<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A calme consolatory view of the sad tempestuous affaires in England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C307</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E384_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201452</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861958</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861958</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114104</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79229)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114104)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 61:E384[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A calme consolatory view of the sad tempestuous affaires in England.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 50, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 19th London".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114104:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114104:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CALME CONSOLATORY View of the ſad tempeſtuous Affaires in <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.7.</bibl>
               <p>Salute Andronicus and Junia my kinſmen, and my fellow-priſoners, who are of note among the Apoſtles, who alſo were in Chriſt before me.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Boetius. Lib. 4. Proſa 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Imperante florenteque Nequitia, Virtus non ſolum Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miis caret, verum etiam ſceleratorum pedibus ſubjecta calca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; in locum facinorum ſupplicia luit; qua fieri in Regno ſcientis omnia, potentis omnia, ſed bene tantummodo volentis, nemo ſatis poteſt vel admirari vel conqueri.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Proſa 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Boni ita ferunt mala inferiora, dum interim à bono ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo non deflectunt; Mali ita bonis fruuntur inferioribus ſummum deperdentes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By Theophilus Craterus.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114104:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114104:2"/>
            <head>To the Criticall Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>oe, ſnarle, and ſpare not; Bite the ſtone till thy teeth breake; if I direct my ſhaft amiſſe, ſtand thou in the Greene, and give aime, meet and receive the blow, and then ſnarle afreſh: yet give me leave to tell thee, Thy very Reprehenſions, which are wont to flye at rovers, if they pitch here, ſhall be imbraced as ſome reward to the attempt; to pleaſe the well-minded, and to offend thee, is an equall honeſt ſuffrage. Yet leſt thou ſhouldeſt in vaine worke out thy owne bowels (for the detracting man ſlayes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in anothers wound) and ſpend all thy venome upon a wrong object (though thou canſt not arreſt my Quill to take Armes againſt it ſelfe, and fight downe that Cauſe which it cryes up) leſt in this ſlender Cottage-Fabrique, thou ſhouldeſt chooſe out ſome inhoſpitable lath of Iriſh wood to lodge thy poyſon in, I will vouchſafe to guide and inſtrust thy ſpleene; if thou wouldeſt have him whom thou trampleſt on, ſubmit to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous conqueſt, and my ſelfe acknowledge thou haſt hit the marke which was ſet up on high, and beyond my reach Prithee tell me, that as ſome Quodlibeticall Juriſts, can put a good face upon a bad cauſe, and ſmooth and curle uglineſſe it ſelfe into a beauty: So, how faire and rich ſoever the matter I treat of be, in its owne pure lineaments, and the ample dowry with which the hand of God hath inſtated it, yet my own plain ſhallowneſſe is ſo unproportionable to that depth and thoſe graces, that what I write, like the Cuttles blacke Stratagem does but veyle the Angell of Light, and diſcolour the cleare ſtreame with darke ſhadowes: If this be it, <hi>Hem porro! ſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum attigiſti:</hi> yet I muſt needs replead upon thee, to mollifie the harſhneſſe of thy cenſure in this reſpect, that my intire love
<pb facs="tcp:114104:3"/>to the Subject, my deſires being wholly wedded to it, whether it thrive or break in this world (as no otherwiſe regarding the excommunicative divorce of Romiſh Bull, or Engliſh Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, then as frightfull Chimara's to ſtill children) may ſtand up ſome Apology for my unworth in judgement, and my deficiency in that <hi>Dives Vena,</hi> which would be a match more ſuitable (I confeſſe they ſhould be Cherubims of beaten gold, which guard the Arke, yet ſtaves of Shitim-wood have been accepted too.)</p>
            <p>So I remember when ſome in <hi>Plutarch</hi> complained to <hi>Alexander,</hi> that a Miller was alwayes ſpeaking well of him (as if a dull home-ſpun Panegyrique were but a ſcandall well breathed, and a calumny of a better aire, as if a native praiſe would taint a Prince, and that at leaſt it ſhould be fetcht from <hi>Sheba</hi>) the King replied his joy, that there was not ſo much as a Miller, but did love <hi>Alexander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have but one graine more to make up weight, and thy own hand muſt throw it into the ſcales: It is but this, That as thy ſelfe canſt not refraine to daſh and blurre ſuch petty draughts as theſe, with ſcorne and ignominy, only becauſe thy inward thoughts boyle and rage with this diſdaine till they run over, <hi>So out of the abundance of my owne heart, my mouth muſt ſpeake,</hi> eſpecially ſince the former way of uttering it ſelfe is now blockt up, <hi>Praeſtat vel ſic otiotium eſſe quam nihil Agere.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114104:3"/>
            <head>A calme Conſolatory view of the ſad Tempeſtuous affaires in <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y buſineſſe the Title tells you, is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolatory, and not Argumentative; for though I ſometimes make an offer at Proofe and Reaſon, yet I looke upon them but as the <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes two mites,</hi> or the paring of the ſhell; the Treaſure and the Food you have had, and may have from wealthier hands, though I perceive that amongſt ſome, this very Manna hath bred wormes and ſtanke, by reaſon of its long continuance; Hee therefore that will ſtill gape after knotty Proofes, and valid Reaſons, notwithſtanding this prejudicate Caution (for I will not flatter the Printer with a <hi>dry Buſh</hi>) of which I know ſo many have beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready tendered, which could not be untyed, but like that of <hi>Gordius,</hi> only cut aſunder, <hi>Nodum in ſcirpo quaerit.</hi> I write not from the Philoſophers <hi>Schooles,</hi> (which have now changed their Gownes to Swords, and perhaps pray that thoſe Swords may be turned into <hi>Pruning Hookes,</hi> not to lop off a Hereſie, but to feed themſelves with the <hi>ſweat of their brow</hi>) but from the Oratours <hi>Deske,</hi> and no doubt the very ſtraine will tell you, that both the Desk, and he that leanes upon it, are made <hi>ex eodem ſtipite,</hi> ſo that neither of them will riſe up unto a <hi>Mercury;</hi> and indeed what uſe is there of a <hi>Demonſtration?</hi> ſince thoſe, to whom I write, are already ſo really convinced, as not to beleeve that the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114104:4"/>beſt Religion, whereby they may either retaine their Old <hi>Tythes,</hi> or acquire ſome New-faſhioned <hi>Stipend,</hi> nor that ſincereſt <hi>Loyalty</hi> which does neither interrupt, nor <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound</hi> their poſſeſſions, but can quietly part with all, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing the Oxe and the Acre, for an inward wealth, which can never be ſurprized;<note place="margin">2 Tim 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>For which cauſe I alſo ſuffer theſe things, nevertheleſſe I am not aſhamed, for I know whom I have beleeved.</hi> To theſe I ſhould but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and who will not adjudge that loſſe of oyle, to ſhew the luſtre of the Sunne by the dimneſſe of a Taper? I might rather in that <hi>Cynick</hi> ſenſe, goe light my <hi>Noon-day candle,</hi> and ſeek for an <hi>honeſt man</hi> in the open Markets, and places of publique concourſe, ſo many of them have forſaken our Iſland, or elſe becauſe they have lived well, they doe <hi>bene latere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>Their life is hid even here too, with Chriſt in God;</hi> But to thoſe who are either ſtarke blinde, or reſolve to cloſe their eyes, <hi>Nox &amp; dies juxta ſunt,</hi> not the <hi>Moone</hi> only, but the <hi>Sun</hi> it ſelfe is <hi>corpus opacum,</hi> who, if all other phyſicke faile may at leaſt be capable of a <hi>dos</hi> of <hi>Hellebore;</hi> and yet, even Theſe, will have <hi>lofty eyes, and eye lids lifted up,</hi> to ſee and acknowledge, that the intire complexe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, both of Man and Chriſtian, is concerned and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in the <hi>Government, Civill</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> under which he lives; both Tables will be reduced to theſe, of which if I would give you a ſenſible Hieroglyphick (unleſſe even this kinde of Imag'ry be abominable, ſo that the <hi>refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med eye</hi> will not indure to be preacht to) I would only draw the pictures of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre we are well agreed, but many harſh ſcruples, like <hi>pricks in our eyes, and thorns in our ſides,</hi> though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they doe not <hi>naturally grow,</hi> are yet <hi>grafted</hi> upon theſe ſtems, ſuch as theſe.</p>
            <p>When God himſelfe ſhall command me, <hi>Feare thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fear God, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the king. 1 Pet. 2.17.</note> Prov. 30.13. when he ſhall joyne the fears of the <hi>King,</hi> next to that of <hi>himſelfe,</hi> as to intimate how little hee regards God himſelf, who ſlights his neareſt image, betwixt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114104:4"/>whom (like that of <hi>Phydias</hi> and <hi>Minerva</hi>) there is ſuch an affin'd dependency, that the glory of the <hi>Man</hi> cannot be violated, unleſſe the <hi>Deity</hi> ſhare in the defacement; as we know it hath been the practiſe of forraigne Warres to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe a ſcorne, and paſſe a judgement upon the abſent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by hanging up his Pourtrayture <hi>(&amp; quae non cernunt frangere colla volunt)</hi> not to adorne a Roome, but to ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize the very Gibbet with ſo defamed a weight, who at length if he fall into ſuch hands, will in vaine expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late an eſcape, or plead that refuge, <hi>Sed periiſſe ſemel, ſatis eſt.</hi> When this command is amongſt ſome of late, not a Religious, but an abject cowardly feare; when the Moon herſelfe is now out-chang'd, who in all her circuits, never beheld ſuch a univerſall alteration from the Full to the Wane; when ſome Field-practitioners will tell us, that to fight againſt the King, conſiſts with this feare of him, and that none of our changes are underſtood in that text, there is at leaſt ſome heſitation to be allow'd for tender conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; <hi>De vitâ (Aeternâ) nunquam ſatis diu deliberatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the command of God,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>Servants be ſubject to your Maſters with all feare, not only to the good and gentle, but alſo to the froward:</hi> if, Indefinitely to any Maſter, though of inferiour ranke, principally to him, who is <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> or as <hi>Homer</hi> ſtiles his <hi>Jupiter,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Father of us poore under-mortalls, and of them alſo of whom it is ſaid, that <hi>They are Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſome abroad will tell us,<note place="margin">Pſ. 82.6.</note> we muſt not be ſubject to a <hi>Tyrant</hi> (indeed this is a leading caſe, and has no prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that an unmatcht clemencie, unparalleld mildneſſe ſhould be ſtampt with the brand of tyranny) but I had thought a very <hi>Tyrant</hi> alſo might be <hi>froward,</hi> and that <hi>fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe</hi> were the onely exception againſt him, I had thought too, that <hi>Not onely, for wrath, but for conſcience ſake,</hi> would unſcruple all demurres of obedience,<note place="margin">Rom. 13 5.</note> and that humane policy would ſtrike ſaile to expreſſe the Law of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>We are commanded to ſubmit <hi>our ſelves to every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114104:5"/>of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as ſupream,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13.</p>
            <p>Yet there are ſome abroad will put an humane ordinance in the ſcales againſt that of Gods, and make that ballance too not as a power derivative from God (at leaſt <hi>in facto eſſe</hi>) but as inherent and eſſentiall, I doubt not but againſt the wills and deſires of thoſe who <hi>Ordaine;</hi> and they tell us too, what ever the Text ſayes, that in this caſe the King is not ſupreame, but only an equall coordinate power, to which I can aſſigne no more proper portentous reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance then the fabulous relation of ſome bold Naturaliſts of men, whoſe <hi>Heads</hi> ſtood not <hi>upon their ſhoulders,</hi> but <hi>within</hi> their <hi>breaſts:</hi> and though all this be required under the forme of ſo potent a charme-<hi>For the Lords ſake</hi>-yet a miſſe interpretation of ſome humane conſtitutions ſhall evacuate all, let the Apoſtle <hi>charme never ſo ſweetly,</hi> though to my utmoſt apprehenſion, the <hi>Laws of the Land</hi> (or rather the popular ſtreet-gloſſe upon them) are a much diſappor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Commentary on the <hi>word of God;</hi> and when I would underſtand St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> aright, I ſhould count it but a flattering digreſſion to conſult with an <hi>Atturney,</hi> or have recourſe to the <hi>Bar;</hi> nay a peece of ſordid unmanlineſſe to mould my opinion after the <hi>vulgar conception</hi> of their <hi>determinations,</hi> to make the <hi>Law of the Land</hi> the Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and the people the ſquare of That, till the people be the only Orthodox Aggregat Divine, as <hi>Themi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocles</hi> ſon ruled Athens, becauſe his wife ruled him, and his ſon her: the very Poet hath bid the Emperour to ſtand more firme, and not give ground to theſe fond-ſicke weaklings — <hi>Mortalia quaerunt Conſilium;</hi>
               <note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mius Theodoſio.</note> 
               <hi>Certus,Juſſa capeſſe Dei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have purpoſely made choice of St. <hi>Peter</hi> (though the ſame Doctrine ſtreams through every pipe) his Epiſtle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing viſibly generall, unreſtrained to times or perſons, to prevent the empty cavill of ſome (whom I have met ſo vain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly deluded) that what was writ to the Romans, reſpected the then preſent ſtate and face of things, and is now expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114104:5"/>not obligatory in <hi>another climate;</hi> though certainly he had forgot that their <hi>obedience</hi> was injoyned to a <hi>heathen Prince,</hi> to a very <hi>Tyrant;</hi> as far as <hi>perſecution</hi> could make him one, at leaſt <hi>that peece</hi> directed to the Romans, will reach to him alſo, as a linke that drawes the whole chaine after it, <hi>Whatſoever things were written aforehand, were written for our learning,</hi> Rom. 15.4. And certainly God does not take leſſe care of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> under the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> then he did of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> under the <hi>Law;</hi> but I would faine win his full aſſent, and that I may doe it with leſſe difficulty, I will afford him one Text more, whoſe eccho I doubt not but he will ſnatch up at the firſt rebound, in Rom. 4.22.23. <hi>It was imputed to him for righteouſneſſe. Now it was not written for his ſake alone, that it was imputed to him but for us alſo, to whom it ſhall be imputed.</hi> Now if <hi>his</hi> and <hi>my ſalvation</hi> be preacht to us from the imputing of Faith to Abraham for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo <hi>his, and my damnation</hi> are denounc'd (for <hi>eadem eſt ratio contrariorum</hi>) if we impenitently <hi>reſiſt,</hi> in that it is thereupon denounced to the Romans.</p>
            <p>But after all, every man who hath but arrived to one ſentence in Latine, is ready to beat me down with the irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible power of Axiome, the very center in which all their circumferentiall lines are <hi>pointed,</hi> and <hi>unite</hi> themſelves to their maine ſtrength; (in a word, their very King, whom only they will not diſobey) <hi>Salus populi lex ſumma;</hi> It is indeed a cordiall of ſoveraigne uſe, if rightly applied, I will not therefore dare to annull or calumniate its rich influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but allow it, <hi>before competent Judges, in caſes meerly humane,</hi> its liberall unlimited extent and efficacie; but then what thinke you of <hi>Salus ſumma?</hi> of a truth, that rule will only preponderate <hi>in Naturalls;</hi> it will but obliege, and ſway in affaires <hi>ſublunary;</hi> thus far it may goe, and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, unleſſe the <hi>wayes</hi> thereof be proved; for where the <hi>dictates of Heaven</hi> doe interpoſe to pull downe its ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and ſtop its courſe, it is then <hi>ultra ſphaeram activitatis,</hi> and cannot, muſt not, <hi>agere,</hi> being reſolved into one of the Preachers <hi>unities under the Sun;</hi> for it is a rule of the God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114104:6"/>of nature, and therefore much more uncontroulable, that it <hi>is better to ſerve God then man.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.19.5.29</note>
            </p>
            <p>And in all theſe, I foame not out my owne rude thoughts and ſelfe-fancies; I vomit not what ever undigeſted abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Embryowims in my owne rude <hi>Braine.</hi> I have bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter learnt the taske of <hi>ſelf-deniall,</hi> then to beleeve <hi>that ſo Magiſteriall,</hi> as to preſcribe a <hi>delirium</hi> for a <hi>caſe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> to any man, or my ſelfe to lye under its thraldome; nor yet have I <hi>ſo learnt Chriſt,</hi> that becauſe <hi>God does dwell in us,</hi> becauſe to man he has given</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eximiam linguamque capaxque</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ingenium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Manilius de Comites.</note> 
                  <hi>volucremque animum quem denique in unum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Deſcendit Deus atque habitat</hi>—</l>
            </q>
            <p>And by all theſe has diſtinguiſht, and preeminenced us from all his creatures upon earth, that therefore I ſhould blaſpheme God by intituling him to any my owne ſudden, raſh irregular effuſions, and to improve them all <hi>ſupra cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum humanum,</hi> by abaſing that moſt excellent gift of God, and by making ſecret inſpiration a cloake to all my blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes —<hi>Non hae noſtre de pectore voces;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Statius lib. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Ille canit</hi> — but it is hee too in his lowd publique voice, which reaches to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome.</p>
            <p>And yet, if in this caſe that rabble, who make it their diſcourſe and paſtime to <hi>deſpiſe dominions,</hi> who revile Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty by the <hi>Glaſſe,</hi> and till ſuch an <hi>Houre refreſh</hi> themſelves againſt the <hi>King,</hi> if they will <hi>mihi manus dare,</hi> that the King is then only to be relinquiſht, when his Commands run point blanke againſt thoſe of God, which they might learne from the <hi>late Annotations upon the Bible,</hi> as compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing under the word, <hi>Reſiſt not only an open rebellion as Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolons</hi> (and though in that ſtole Comment, they write not the word <hi>King,</hi> yet that alſo is powerfully implyed in the <hi>Rebellion of Abſolon</hi>) but alſo by not yeelding obedience to their command in thoſe things, that are not againſt the word of God; where I would only propoſe this queſtion, that, ſince we muſt not obey the King againſt God, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the King (only of all mankinde) bound to execute
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114104:6"/>that advice, the actuating of which he conceives a breach of his conſcience towards God? I confeſſe I underſtand not, nor yet am ſo inextricably <hi>irratus in verba Magiſtri,</hi> as ſtubbornely to reſiſt a convincing reaſon, if yet they will, by drawing thus neare (like a leape revearſt) flye further backe—<hi>tam prope, tam proculque</hi>—and aſſume that his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands runne thus; yet the common rumours (which is the guiſe of thoſe who afflict Innocence) by the charge only in Generalls; my eares have not yet tingled with the relation of This or That, yet my owne experience of his Religious deportment towards his God (which no doubt will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced in Gods <hi>time here,</hi> or unfailably in Gods <hi>eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hereafter</hi>) will incourage me to avouch thus far (his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition atteſting it to be no peece of remote flattery) that there is not that Prince under heaven, who devotes himſelfe with more zeale (and that, ſuch as St. <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, <hi>according to knowledge</hi>) with more holy debates and inquiries after the grounds and depth of truth, to the immaculate ſervice of the great God; nor indeed doe I at all wonder, that after ſo <hi>ſolid ſettlements,</hi> and ſo elaborate <hi>trialls of the ſpirits,</hi> he ſhould not now <hi>ſhake and waver in the faith,</hi> I ſhould rather wonder if he did; and certainly he who relented at the errour of <hi>Star-chamber,</hi> and <hi>High Commiſſion,</hi> at <hi>Ship-money, &amp;c.</hi> will not be pertinacious in any point of <hi>Religion,</hi> of which his <hi>conſcience</hi> ſhall bee perſwaded, that it is <hi>erroneous,</hi> the upholding of which would be prejudiciall to him in that <hi>Court</hi> where he is only lyable to anſwer as much more as the Heavens are better then the Earth; in ſuch a caſe he will eaſily remember, and tranſcribe the high patterne from whence he is deſcended, riſing up with as forward and pregnant a flame for <hi>Gods owne</hi> immediate honour, as his Royall Father (of ever bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed memory, whoſe halcion dayes God reſtore amongſt us) did for the honour of his Church; who when the <hi>ſanctum ſanctorum</hi> was vilified into his <hi>Wardrope,</hi> and the Prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion preacht freely downe by the Parſon of that Church to his owne Sacred eares, the ſame day ſwore him Chaplaine
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114104:7"/>for his integrity, which made the <hi>righteous man bold as a Lion,</hi> and commanded a quick remove of all his Robes, of his ſhooes (if any were there) <hi>becauſe the ground is holy.</hi> Yet I confeſſe (though I would never ſpeake of a <hi>King</hi> but with reverence, and preſume I doe that too, whilſt I only prefer <hi>God</hi> before him; neither <hi>Pope</hi> nor <hi>people</hi>) ſhould a ſlip in this kinde, poſſibly eſcape him (as much as I eſteem Monarchy, and priſe the gift at <hi>Plinys</hi> owne rate, <hi>Nullum praſtabilius aut pulchrius munus Dei quam caſtus, &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus &amp; Deo ſimillimus princeps</hi>) I would wave my obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence here,<note place="margin">In Panegit. ad Tr.</note> and ſubmit to heaven, becauſe as upon Earth, though I muſt ſubmit to other governours,<note place="margin">1 Pet 2.14.</note> as unto them that are ſent by him, yet I muſt ſubmit to the King as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame; thus as the King is head of the people, ſo as the King is Vicegerent to God, though I muſt ſubmit to the King as being ſent by him (<hi>For by him Kings reigne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 8.15. Dan. 2.22.</note> it is he that ſetteth them up) ſo I muſt ſubmit to God as ſupream governour of all the world, <hi>for he is a God of Gods, and a Lord of Kings:</hi> and where the commands of theſe claſh and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfere, where they are not <hi>ſubordinate,</hi> but <hi>contradiſtinct,</hi> becauſe I cannot obey both, I muſt deſert my <hi>Prince,</hi> and this is more my <hi>duty</hi> then <hi>diſloyalty:</hi> the Philoſopher hath markt it with his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;<note place="margin">Epictet. c. 18.</note> which is the ſenſe of our Saviour himſelf upon the Mount (the very place elevating our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and being it ſelf part of the Sermon) <hi>No man can ſerve two Maſters, for he will hold to the one, and deſpiſe the other,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.24.</note> 
               <hi>ye cannot ſerve God and Mammon:</hi> In the higheſt and only inſtance, it is not, <hi>I doe not</hi> obey my King, but I <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not;</hi> yet even in this, I would be loath to bee altogether <hi>diſ-ſubjected;</hi> I will ſtill obey him <hi>paſſively,</hi> according to the moſt commendable example of Scripture, and the pureſt practice of the Primitive times under the Heathen perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute s, and not <hi>vim vi repellere:</hi> neither would I ſo much as bring a <hi>rayling accuſation</hi> againſt him: the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Daniel</hi> hath taught me a more ſuitable addreſſe even from the <hi>Lyons den,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 21.</note> 
               <hi>O King live for ever!</hi> nay were I to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114104:7"/>ſpeake with him from Gods owne mouth, and to reforme his errors againſt heaven it ſelf, though in all caſes, this alone would admit of the harſheſt reproofe, yet even in this caſe (though I am well aware, that ſuch particular commands are now expired, and that the <hi>written word</hi> is the only <hi>rule</hi> of <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi>) an humble intreaty ſhould be my ſevereſt reprehenſion; it ſhould be, with the Prophet <hi>Jeremy, Obey I beſeech thee, the voice of the Lord which I ſpeake unto thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ch 38. v. 20.</note> 
               <hi>and with St.</hi> Paul, <hi>I know thee, O King, to be expert in all cuſtomes and queſtions, wherefore I beſeech thee to heare mee patiently;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 26.3.</note> nay ſhould I dare to queſtion him in principles, and fundamentalls of Religion, <hi>King Agrippa, beleeveſt thou the Prophets?</hi> I would quarrell downe my owne boldneſſe and ſubjoyne St. <hi>Pauls</hi> checke upon my too forward inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, <hi>I know that thou beleeveſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.27.</note> elſe if I ſet my tongue looſe to <hi>ſpeake evill</hi> of ſo high a <hi>diguity,</hi> be my <hi>cauſe</hi> never ſo good, and my <hi>affliction</hi> never ſo great, the King does but <hi>perſecute</hi> me, and I the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And throughout all this my intention is very farre from defaming any of thoſe Honourable Members of either Houſe, who are ſummoned by the Kings Writ, and the Kings Authority, to conſult <hi>de arduis Reip: Negotiis:</hi> the Heathen himſelfe will teach me better Divinity, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">Tat. 9. lib. ult.</note> whoſe ever curioſity or prejudicateneſſe ſhall cull out a <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell</hi> hence, becauſe he would be thought <hi>profound,</hi> and ſuch a one as can ſearch and pierce deeper then common eyes, if he will needs <hi>ſwim</hi> where he ſhould but <hi>wade,</hi> whilſt hee does thus <hi>Male recitare</hi> without the expenſe of a new printed <hi>Diſclaimer,</hi> I doe already diſavow the <hi>Adulterated ſheets</hi> and lay them at his doore, as being become the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding author.</hi> I dare boldly hope who ever ſhall ſuſpect thoſe great and high names of ſiniſter deſignes upon the Kings honour and power (for there is no place ſo high, not the very Throne, no perſon ſo upright, not the very King, but theſe wild dayes will calumniate) of hollow jugling, proteſtations to God and all the world, that they did never
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114104:8"/>really intend to contrive our Dread Soveraigne into the moſt <hi>flouriſhing Prince in Chriſtendome,</hi> that all their many, many Declarations did but veile their owne politique ends under ſo glorious a maske of <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>ſincerity,</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging themſelves no leſſe then <hi>humble and loyall Subjects</hi> from that place of <hi>Judicature,</hi> where they are as <hi>great</hi> as <hi>earth</hi> can make them: I dare boldly hope the time is now hard at hand, in which it will appeare <hi>all this was no maske,</hi> but their very face, no <hi>forgid</hi> comelineſſe, but a native un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>painted glory, and that <hi>Aaron, and all the children of Iſrael ſhall ſee Moſes and behold the skin of his face to ſhine alſo;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod 34.30.</note> that their often <hi>atteſting</hi> God, and adjuring us by ſo great a Name,<note place="margin">Jerem. 42.5.</note> 
               <hi>ſo true and faithfull a witneſſe,</hi> ſo juſt and revenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a <hi>Judge</hi> of <hi>Falſhood</hi> in ſuch an <hi>act</hi> eſpecially, and ſuch an <hi>omiſſion</hi> being circumſtanced up to ſo high a nature by the <hi>Repreſentative Nationall</hi> capacity of the joynt-perſons, whereby the <hi>Honour of God</hi> (of which he is ſo <hi>jealous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 34.14.</note> that it is his very Name,<note place="margin">Eſa: 42 8.48.32.</note> and which he will not impart to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) would not barely ſuffer, but be led <hi>captive</hi> and <hi>inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> upon as <hi>conquered</hi> and <hi>invaſſalled to a greater honour,</hi> will be lookt backe upon as a Religious <hi>vow</hi> and <hi>Propheſie,</hi> and their preſent immediate actions conſpire into a devout <hi>performance and lively fulfilling</hi> of them, which otherwiſe would be but a <hi>dead,</hi> nay a <hi>killing letter,</hi> let any foule mouth ſpeake what infection it pleaſe; Such Wiſe men cannot but conſider, that the <hi>intereſt</hi> of a whole Kingdome is involved in ſuch <hi>Publique Vows,</hi> and by the <hi>violation</hi> of them, and the <hi>Majeſty of God</hi> muſt lye at ſtake, gaſping for the <hi>dregs of Gods laſt judgements,</hi> and ſuch <hi>good men will not</hi> but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſo <hi>univerſall a miſchiefe,</hi> ſo that I will not feare under the conduct of ſuch Pilots, a ſudden <hi>Tranſmigration,</hi> a <hi>new living</hi>— <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that without croſſing the Seas, wee ſhould all ſtart up Ruſſians and Aethiopians, not that our glory will be extinguiſht at home, which ſhines ſo cleare abroad:<note place="margin">Doctrus p. 80.</note> for the <hi>Italian,</hi> (or elſe his <hi>Favourable tranſlator</hi>) ingenuouſly preferring us to all the world, does give us this generous marke of diſparity from thoſe (becauſe amongſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114104:8"/>them, <hi>There is nothing worthy of obſervation, more then the Tyrannous controuling of Lawes, and the immediate proſtitution of all ſorts to the imperious will of the Prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler;</hi> and againe, <hi>Anglia libera Gens:</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 94.</note> As my buſineſſe will be anon to incourage thoſe, who have loſt their Fleece for their owne conſcience ſake, to ſuffer <hi>Cheerfully,</hi> not only ſo, but that they would <hi>Frui Diis Iratis,</hi> take poſſeſſion of their loſſe, and injoy their misfortunes, not only ſo neither, but that they would <hi>poſſeſſe their owne ſoules alſo in their patience,</hi> without which a man is beſides himſelfe,<note place="margin">Luke 21.19.</note> and not a man: ſo it is now, that they would not foreſtall the <hi>great Court</hi> by unwotthy feares, but ſuſpend a while, and in imitation of the meeke <hi>Lambe of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa 53 7. Acts 8 32. v. 3. v. 10.</note> 
               <hi>not open their mouths before the ſhearers,</hi> and ſee if like <hi>Jobs,</hi> their flocks and herds will not be returned with intereſt, <hi>the ſeven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand in the firſt Chapter, to foureteen thouſand in the laſt:</hi> for my owne part, though I am much of their perſwaſion (and pray ſtill that I may be ſo) who can like the reſolved Emperour, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and if I ſtray in judgement bee content to doe penance here to the utmoſt farthing, that I may eſcape the eternall priſon by an Involuntary unbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain'd deviation, yet I freely confeſſe my ſelfe ſo <hi>compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately guiltfull;</hi> that tranſgreſſions are ſo twiſted round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout me, that I am <hi>ty'd and bound with the chaines of</hi> them; that I <hi>have drawne iniquity with cords of vanity,</hi> and have <hi>ſinned as it were with a cart rope;</hi> and againe,<note place="margin">Eſa. 5.18.</note> with that <hi>rope</hi> have pluckt downe vengeance from heaven upon this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that I muſt confeſſe (what evill ſoever ſome men may call it) there is no <hi>malum paenae in the City but the Lord hath done it;</hi> and if any ſhall aske me,<note place="margin">Amos 3.6.</note> hath not my wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe cryed aloud for this ſcourge? ſome charitable man may returne this anſwer, in an humble aſtoniſht ſenſe, <hi>And he was ſpeechleſſe,</hi> I had rather ſtrike my guilty breaſt, then make a Phariſaicall Oration of innocence, who have nothing elſe of <hi>good</hi> in me, but the acknowledgement of my <hi>ill,</hi> and the juſtice of God upon it, and this may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps intitle me to ſome one quality of <hi>Seneca's</hi> Goodman,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114104:9"/>
               <hi>Quicquid viro bono accidit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt 76.</note> 
               <hi>aequo animo ſuſtinobit; ſciet enim id accidiſſe lege divina qua univerſa procedunt.</hi> In ſuch a caſe of trialls the very Atheiſt (like the Apoſtate Julian with his <hi>Viciſti Galilaee</hi>) leaves out himſelfe, and ſets up a God,<note place="margin">Lucian. 1 Tom Timon.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which old repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant <hi>Eli,</hi> upon Gods ſentence againſt him, hath indenizon'd into a Scripture-expreſſion,<note place="margin">Sam. 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>It is the Lord, let him doe what ſeemeth him good:</hi> and if we may apply another orthodox ſenſe to the ſame words (the practiſe both of the ancient Fathers, and of the Moderne moſt learned devout Writers,) It is our Saviours almoſt literally, <hi>It is I, be not afraid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From what I have hitherto ſaid,<note place="margin">Mat. 14.27.</note> as the ſevereſt eye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſcerne a quarrell againſt my King, to whom there is not only an obligation laid upon my words, but my very thoughts are alſo tyed up;<note place="margin">Eccles. 10 20.</note> ſo I hope, no moderate indifferent man will arraign any piece of my language againſt his great Court; I know I am bound there alſo, for <hi>Thou ſhalt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile the Gods</hi> (i.e.) as ſome read the Judges;<note place="margin">Exod. 22 28.</note> I would faine perſwade my ſelfe, that at leaſt, that one ingredient of an intire Chriſtian, ſpreads it ſelfe throughout my ſpirituall compoſition, to love the whole world, I meane the perſons, for I was never baptized into that hatred, and would bee loath (which in another kinde of contraries, is the divells talleſt ſtratagem to ſtir up and inflame a contentfull pride out of humility it ſelfe) to make my love of one (though of him who is the very breath of our noſtrills, and whoſe ſafety is worth ten thouſand of us) protect,<note place="margin">Lament. 4.20. 2 Sam 18.3.</note> and patronage my contempt of ſome others.</p>
            <p>In the next place, give me leave to ſpeake a few words in the behalfe of my languiſhing mother, the Church, and you ſhall have them as from a true ſonne of the Church, in the ſpirit of meekneſſe.</p>
            <p>In which there are three points of moment, which ſtruggle for the Truth; <hi>Power of Ordination, Juriſdiction, and Diſcipline:</hi> The two former I conceive to be eſſentially in the <hi>Biſhops as ſucceeding the Apoſtles;</hi> for the latter I humbly conceive the forme already eſtabliſht by <hi>full act of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114104:9"/>Parliament,</hi> to be the pureſt in Chriſtendome: All theſe I ſhall now much wrong, as being removed from the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of bookes, which led me away a willing captive to them my unconſtrained opinions, having not taſted the edge of any ſword, but that of the Spirit which hath ſubdued my very minde, yet I ſhall venture upon the ſtrength of that reaſon, <hi>quae nec decipitur, nec decipit unquam,</hi> at leaſt to wooe a Toleration of them.</p>
            <p>I have ſome Scripture by me for the former, though I wiſh I could readily recall thoſe other texts alſo, which have ſo irrefragably convinced my aſſent.</p>
            <p>In the 6 of Acts and the 2. <hi>The twelve called the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of diſciples unto them, and ſaid,</hi> v. 3. <hi>Seeke ye out among you men of honeſt report, full of the Holy Ghoſt and wiſedome, whom we may appoint over this buſineſſe:</hi> which Dr. <hi>Gerhard</hi> applyes to the Ordination of Deacons, and if to the appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>them</hi> the care of the Apoſtles did deſcend, much more to the appointing of Prieſts or Presbyters, being a <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Order;</hi> it is the kinde of argument <hi>à fortiori,</hi> with which our Saviour himſelfe does incourage his Apoſtles, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the feare of Perſecution and death it ſelfe. <hi>The very haires of your heads are all numbered, Feare yee not therefore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat 27.30.</note> 
               <hi>not them that can kill the body;</hi> nor did the Apoſtles only do this, but the injunction lay upon their ſucceſſours the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, upon <hi>Timothy</hi> the firſt Biſhop of the Church of the Epheſians, <hi>Lay hands ſuddenly on no man: upon Titus the firſt Biſhop of the Church of the Cretians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ep. 5 c. 22. v.</note> 
               <hi>For this cauſe left I thee in Crete that thou ſhouldeſt ordaine Elders in every City.</hi> The caſe is thus farre plaine; that it hath been ſo,<note place="margin">1 Ch. 5 v.</note> it is plainer yet, that it may be ſo, by the Conceſſion of the greateſt Divine-Antagoniſts, who having received their <hi>orders from ſuch hands,</hi> performe their <hi>Miniſteriall</hi> functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without any new qualification. Now ſince their power is confeſt lawfull on all hands, and <hi>neceſſary</hi> on ſome, the deſigne certainly of <hi>inlarging the Kingdome of Chriſt, and ſetting up his throne in the hearts of men,</hi> might goe on more cheerfully, whilſt that way of receiving it, is indulged to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114104:10"/>thoſe thouſands who can no otherwayes receive it. It is as true as Scripture, <hi>Except we eat the fleſh of the Sonne of man and drinke his bloud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">St John 6.35.</note> 
               <hi>we have no life in us.</hi> That fleſh and blood are imparted in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> that <hi>Euchariſt</hi> by the Miniſters of the Word; that thoſe whom the <hi>Biſhops ordain,</hi> can adminiſter the <hi>Sacrament</hi> is granted by All, that thoſe who are otherwayes ordained, cannot ſay alſo that they are not <hi>ordained,</hi> is beleeved by many (by very much the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of Chriſtendome) and what then ſhall become of thoſe many ſoules, who hunger and thirſt to be thus made righteous, who paſſionately cry out, <hi>Lord evermore give us this bread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 34.</note> when they beleeve the Hand that reaches it out, might to as good purpoſe hold forth a ſtone? and when they call for this <hi>blood</hi> to drinke, they ſhall only finde that the <hi>Well is deep, and there is nothing to draw:</hi> Certainly this is not ſuch a <hi>common dyet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 4 6. 1 King. 17.6.</note> that with the Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> wee ſhould be beholden to the <hi>Ravens</hi> to bring us <hi>bread and fleſh in the morning</hi> (that bread which is fleſh alſo) I meane ſuch of whom wee ſuſpect they have nothing elſe of the Prieſt about them, but the <hi>black</hi> they weare: I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I proceed, but humbly deſire the Reader to be as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall as my ſelfe, and not to conceive any thing here to be diſpatcht by an Incendiary, but from a conſcience which groans under theſe very preſſures, and poures it ſelfe out to heaven for a reliefe. I would not (like her who dreamt herſelfe with childe of a Firebrand) adde the leaſt ſparke to the combuſtion already made, but only beg a plaiſter for the ſores and ſcorchings which rankle and feſter our <hi>ſoule,</hi> in the beſt part of it, our <hi>minde:</hi> when thou haſt beleeved my ſincere purpoſe, I may goe on to tell thee, that if we looke upon all <hi>Chriſtendome and all antiquity, the univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of time and place</hi> will be out loud Advocates: if I ſhould tell a <hi>heathen,</hi> who like <hi>King Agrippa, was almoſt perſwaded to be a Chriſtian,</hi> how much the Church of Rome agrees with us, it ſhould be no diſadvantage to the <hi>Generall Cauſe,</hi> and it ſhould have moment too amongſt our ſelves, wherein we are at <hi>one,</hi> unleſſe with the <hi>Invocation of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> we would
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114104:10"/>alſo renounce the <hi>calling upon God,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay, <hi>Our Father,</hi> eſpecially (which had its full operation upon that learned compacted friend of Truth, and enemy of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh errour) that our acknowledgement muſt render unto God, the things that are Gods,<note place="margin">Sir Edwin Sands in ſpec. Eur. p. 77.</note> conſidering that all <hi>good things</hi> are from God, though they be found in his very <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> but amongſt the <hi>Reformed,</hi> how lately has that <hi>Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall</hi> extirpation prevailed in what a <hi>Nooke</hi> of the earth? He that remembers not when it was <hi>rooted and brancht</hi> out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> is but yet a childe; (he that can tell me what <hi>bleſſings</hi> that Kingdome hath ſince injoy'd beſides <hi>Engliſh gold and the impoveriſhment of her ſiſter,</hi>) <hi>erit mihi magnus Apollo:</hi> for the <hi>Reformed</hi> part of <hi>France,</hi> I remember lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Moulin,</hi> about ſix years ſince, has printed their <hi>deſires for Epiſcopacy,</hi> and their <hi>ſubmiſſion only</hi> to this <hi>fatall neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> that becauſe there cannot be <hi>two Biſhops</hi> of <hi>one Dioceſſe,</hi> and becauſe, in that Government there muſt be a <hi>Popiſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,</hi> the <hi>Reformed</hi> part muſt therefore onely <hi>wiſh</hi> that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe which they cannot <hi>injoy</hi> is for another <hi>Reformed</hi> Church, I remember their <hi>printed prayer,</hi> That God would have mercy upon them in this behalfe, for their want of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and the Comment upon it, that whereas they deſire mercy, they acknowledge the offence. For our ſelves (I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire pardon for ſuch a ſolemne Truth, as needing no freſh wound, ſince I <hi>bleed</hi> whilſt I ſpeak it) if <hi>that government</hi> were <hi>aboliſht</hi> by the ſame <hi>full power which ſo frequently ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> (though with humility, I ſpeake it, long ſince <hi>Statu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt</hi> irreverſibly in the <hi>Law of God,</hi> and to ſuch <hi>Lawes</hi> I preſume thoſe of the Land, did never intend a <hi>confirmation</hi> by way of <hi>authority,</hi> becauſe they ſtand already upon a <hi>fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Baſis,</hi> but declare their <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi>) it would be a griefe as irremedileſſe as unſupportable; but <hi>rebus ſic ſtantibus,</hi> the <hi>Aequilibrium</hi> is much doubted, when the party of one profeſt contrary opinion, are the Judges and executioners of the other, the Aſſertors of it being yet unexamined whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they can plead not guilty, it is a <hi>juſt ſentence</hi> even againſt a <hi>juſt ſentence, parte inandita altera Aequum lices ſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rit
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114104:11"/>hand Aequus eſt,</hi> be they never ſo right in the <hi>bonum,</hi> the want of the <hi>bone</hi> ſpoyles all; it is a caſe not much unlike which we reprehend (and muſt for ever) in the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> That which is a <hi>ſtigma</hi> to them, will ſcarce become our <hi>ornament, &amp; decere Curios:</hi> I cannot but well reliſh the ingenuity of the Oratour, <hi>Cum de Religione agitur. T. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runcanum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicero de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turâ Deorum Lib. 3.</note> 
               <hi>P. Scipionem P. Scavolam, Pontificis Maximis non Zenonem aut Cleanthem aut Chryſipum ſequor;</hi> As in point of Religion hee would not take advice from the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers morality (though that toucht the borders of the garment, till they almoſt kiſt each other) ſo they ſhould not be only <hi>Pontifices,</hi> but <hi>Maximi,</hi> whom hee would have recourſe to; I cannot ſo far captivate my judgement, but <hi>this</hi> will ſtill be a <hi>ſtumbling blocke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For theſe reaſons, and for many other, I would gladly liſten to, at leaſt a <hi>Toleration of their Government, and the old forme of prayers</hi> (which ſhould not like us that uſe them, <hi>decay</hi> for having <hi>liv'd ſo long,</hi> but grow more <hi>vigorous</hi> from their very age, if it were not a <hi>principle</hi> remov'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the <hi>danger of proofe,</hi> why <hi>God will ever be,</hi> I would give this reaſon, becauſe <hi>God alwayes was</hi>) and this, not only to ſatisfie my <hi>Oaths,</hi> (which as one well ſayes of friendſhip, <hi>Amare Non cito deſiſto, non temere incipio,</hi> ſhould not be taken without deliberation, nor forgone with raſhneſſe: and as another, <hi>Let thy acquaintance be many,</hi> but thy <hi>friends few,</hi> though I may reſolve often becauſe thoſe may be <hi>broken,</hi> and my <hi>faith</hi> ſtand <hi>whole,</hi> yet I would <hi>ſeldome ſweare,</hi> becauſe a <hi>Violation of that</hi> will <hi>waſte</hi> my <hi>conſcience</hi>) but alſo that I might obtaine the ſame equall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from my <hi>Brother-Proteſtants,</hi> which has ſometimes been indulged our Religion from the harſheſt enemies of <hi>it and us,</hi> nothing ſo cruell as to be wounded by thoſe of our owne Houſe. <hi>Quod tu facias, hoc mihi paete dolet,</hi> a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration to all thoſe of the <hi>Auguſtane Confeſſion</hi> was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Emperour in <hi>Conventu Ratisbon. anno</hi> 1532. nay by the Pope himſelfe,<note place="margin">Lampad. Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lific. p. 429.</note> 
               <hi>anno</hi> 1533. <hi>Pontifex Clemens miſit legatum Hugonem Randonem ad Saxoniae Ducem Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorem
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114104:11"/>Proteſtantem,</hi> by whom he ſignifi'd the Grant, it was the very yeare, in which King <hi>Henry</hi> 8 <hi>did deficere a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa,</hi> and our whole Kingdome became generally <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> ſo that it is not any bold upſtart, vnhear'd of ſuite, but what has been approov'd, allow'd, countenanc't by repeated <hi>Acts of Proteſtant-Parliaments,</hi> if yet the <hi>Commencers</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are branded with the Idolatrous name of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> they are only ſuch who will <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> and <hi>preach,</hi> and <hi>write</hi> againſt them, though <hi>Death</hi> ſtand in the gap, and <hi>ſwim in the Prophets pots;</hi> beſides, none can tell how much it would aſſwage the heats and riſings within, how it would ſtop the mouthes of many againſt Oppreſſion, in opening them to their God. But to attempt a very ſcripturall reaſon, and at leaſt by conſequence, and rationall deduction, to ſhew that this requeſt is agreeable to the Chriſtian Policy of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Paul, who, in Acts 15, forbad blood, and things ſtrangled to be eaten, only to comply with the Half-won Jew, that he might be wholly Chriſtian; now let the caſe be ballanc't; the abſtinence from thoſe was fully abrogated by the infallible Authority of Chriſt Himſelfe; I doubt not but the modeſty of each Abrogatour here, will acknowledge himſelfe ſingly, and the whole body to be fallible, becauſe men; the permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted abſtinence from blood (under colour of Religion and conſcience) was as oppoſite to Evangelicall Doctrine, as Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſme to Chriſtianity; ſuch a difference betwixt obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not-obſervation of our Ancient Liturgy, was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet mentioned; and that this is not the drift and ſenſe of the Authour only, but of the preſent Aſſembly: you have the whole of it, at leaſt collaterally in their Annotations, the words are; he ſheweth that theſe Ceremonies, to what they were accuſtomed many yeeres, could not without great diſtractions be aboliſht, untill they could better learne their liberty in Chriſt. and that the word <hi>Neceſſary,</hi> v. 28. is not to be referred to the Ceremonies themſelves, but to the preſent occaſion and perſons; I will not purſue my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe from the word <hi>accuſtomed,</hi> nor from the, <hi>ſuddainely,</hi> but leave it to the judgement of any ſingle eye, whether
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114104:12"/>there be not fairer, at leaſt <hi>tolerability,</hi> in all reſpects, for this, then for thoſe.</p>
            <p>That there ſhould be a <hi>ſub</hi> and <hi>ſupra,</hi> in the Church I conceive equitable from the difference in parts and abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, not onely of the ſame <hi>kinde,</hi> though not of the ſame <hi>degree;</hi> but if the gifts be ſeverally look't upon, wee ſhall finde them not only <hi>gradually,</hi> but <hi>ſpecifically</hi> diſtinct, and I am well aware of my own inſufficiency either way, which would eaſily perſwade my <hi>Canonicall Obedience</hi> to the abler man.<note place="margin">Cor 12 28.</note> 
               <hi>God hath ſet forth ſome, firſt Apoſtles, &amp;c.</hi> and then he preſently askes, <hi>are all Apoſtles? are all Prophets? &amp;c.</hi> from which Method I ſuppoſe I may reaſonably conclude, that God hath ſet forth ſome more peculiarly inabled by one gift, then others, and therefore thinke it unfit to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually claimed by all. Wee are already in a <hi>Conflagration;</hi> but we may remember that the whole <hi>world</hi> was ſet on <hi>fire,</hi> when the <hi>Novice-Phaeton</hi> would needs <hi>hold the Reines,</hi> and <hi>miſguide the Chariot of the Sun:</hi> If yet this <hi>Parlty</hi> muſt be inforc't, I would deſire <hi>that Church-man</hi> to rumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the reply of <hi>Lycurgus</hi> (one of the wiſeſt <hi>Legiſlators</hi> that ever ſate at Sterne) who, when he was ſollicited to ſet up a Democracy, ſlack't the importunity of the raſh advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer with a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: whereupon he went away, like <hi>the rich man</hi> in the Goſpel, <hi>very penſive for he had many Servants,</hi> and ſhall <hi>Gods Houſe</hi> indure that confuſed <hi>Anarchy</hi> which thy owne abhorres? Certainely, if wee thinke it meet to tranſcribe from Heaven, wee ſhall finde that without repining of the <hi>ſtarres,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 10.</note> God made <hi>two great Lights, the Sun to rule the day, and the Moone to rule the night,</hi> and ſhall it be otherwiſe with thoſe who are called <hi>the Light of the world? Shall the ſeven Golden Candleſtickes be remooved,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat 5 14. Rev. 2 22.</note> or elſe a <hi>Blazing Star,</hi> or a <hi>Ruſh</hi> be put into them? Nay, in Heaven, amongſt the very <hi>ſtars,</hi> one differs from another in glory, and when your ſelves come thither,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> though every one of you ſhall be <hi>full</hi> of glory; yet there ſhall be a <hi>different</hi> meaſure accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your ſeverall <hi>Capacities</hi> (Chriſt hath told us there
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114104:12"/>ſhall be a <hi>leaſt in the Kingdome of Heaven</hi>) and I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where read it well illuſtrated by glaſſes of a different ſize,<note place="margin">Math. 11.11.</note> dived into the River, of which though one holds <hi>more,</hi> none is <hi>fuller</hi> then another, the <hi>Amphora</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rcens</hi> are both <hi>brimmed up,</hi> and therefore no <hi>roome</hi> either for more <hi>Drops</hi> into it ſelfe, or for <hi>Envy</hi> at anothers ſtreame, to which I may apply that of Seneca, <hi>Hic plus edit, ille mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, quid refert? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iam ſatur eſt, hic plus bibit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 85.</note> 
               <hi>ille minus, quid refert? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> non ſitit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet if the <hi>Epiſcopall word</hi> be only excepted at, as I have heard ſome moderate judging adverſaries, give in their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit, that the <hi>Authority muſt</hi> be retained, or elſe <hi>themſelves ſhall fall out with any new intruſion</hi>) <hi>and the name and thing</hi> may ſtill be allowed us, if a <hi>Paſtour or a ſuper-intendent (the Latine-Engliſh of</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſhall turne out the Notion, and leave behind the <hi>Rem ſubſtratam,</hi> I ſhould not much ſtraine at it, (though I know not how juſtly queazy others might be) and feare the <hi>Title</hi> be onely parted with, as an <hi>Earneſt,</hi> that all the <hi>Appendages</hi> ſhall follow, though any <hi>Bargaine</hi> may be legally evacuated with the <hi>loſſe of Earneſt</hi>) ſuch a <hi>Gnat,</hi> though with reluctancy, wee might perhaps at length <hi>ſwallow,</hi> though the other <hi>Camell</hi> would down-right <hi>choake</hi> us, and like the <hi>Picture of Jonah,</hi> in the <hi>Whales mouth,</hi> ſtick in our <hi>throat</hi> for ever; it would neither <hi>feede</hi> us it ſelfe, and would alſo ſtop up the <hi>Avenew,</hi> that no other <hi>ſuſtenance</hi> might have <hi>paſſage;</hi> in this caſe I ſhould bleſſe God for one of <hi>Jobs Meſſengers,</hi> that the <hi>Caldeans had fell upon theſe and the like Camells, and carryed them all away,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 1.17.</note> as fearing alſo that ſuch Beaſts of ſpace and compaſſe, might <hi>fill up the narrow way, and lie as another Gate</hi> before the <hi>ſtrait-gate of Heaven</hi> to lock us out.<note place="margin">Math. 7.14.</note> But it is of late ſaid by the Compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the <hi>Annotations upon the whole Bible,</hi> that this kind of Cleargy is inclined to Popery,<note place="margin">Preface pag. 2.</note> and have uſed meanes for the introduction of it (that I may not over-expreſſe any thing, and my relation be charged with malice, I will give it you in their owne language, which is, of it ſelfe, ſo high that I confeſſe I have not fancy enough to ſoare at that rate)
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114104:13"/>
               <hi>And if ever thoſe Maſters of the Myſtery of iniquity (having a long ſince ſet on foote their deſigne to make the Kingdome retrograde in Religion, in turning toward the Tenets of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Forme of Worſhip of the Romiſh Church) have any cauſe to mount it on horſebacke, it muſt be by putting downe the moſt found, ſincere, and zealous preaching of the Word, as by ſome experimentall preparations wee have ſeene of late, and our reaſon may fore-ſee and fore-caſt for the time to come, for this hath been, and it is like may be hereafter their manner, who labour to extinguiſh (at leaſt to eclipſe) the light of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicall Doctrine; firſt, by picking a quarrell with the moſt ſufficient, diligent, and conſcionable Preachers, to ſtop their mouthes, impriſon their perſons, or to drive them from their Country— Pudet haec opprobria</hi>— a heavy charge I confeſſe to betray the truth, but ſince the bare <hi>aſſertion</hi> is the whole <hi>argument,</hi> I ſhall thinke it an honeſt payment to returne that Romiſh anſwer— <hi>Ais, Nego,</hi> unleſſe themſelves introduce a Doctrine of the <hi>R. Church,</hi> and ſpeake <hi>infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly;</hi> yet, if theſe kinde of men thus inſimulated of <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> have not beene the ſtouteſt Propugners of our Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> many of them by writing, ſome by ſealing the Truth with their blood, I have read no books, to the meanes they are ſaid to uſe, for the incompaſſement of ſo darke a deſigne, I will not returne that anſwere, <hi>Quid minus eſt, non dico Oratoris, ſed hominis, quam id objicere Aduerſario,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tull. Philip. 2.</note> 
               <hi>quod ille ſi verbo negarit longius progredi non poſſit, qui objecerit,</hi> the times give me another reply, and I am ſorry I muſt <hi>par pari referre,</hi> lay downe payment in the ſame coyne — <hi>Mutato nomine de te fabula narratur; that many ſound ſincere, and zealous Preachers are put downe; that the mouthes of the moſt ſufficient, diligent, conſcionable Preachers are ſtopt; that the perſons of many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned here, and many others have got leave to be driven out of their Country. Servi ut taceant, Jumenta loquentur, &amp; Canis, &amp; Poſtes, &amp; Marmora</hi> — of which, though wee, who are yours, and would be their <hi>Servants in Chriſt,</hi> ſhould be as ſilent to you, as wee are to our <hi>Flocke, the ſtone out of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114104:13"/>wall ſhall cry, and the beame out of the timber ſhall anſwer it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Habak 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> for want of the Antiphonaries, the <hi>Vox clamantis</hi> in the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and the <hi>reſponſals</hi> of the <hi>people;</hi> for that at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent there are many hundred Churches in England lye ſpeechleſſe, or have no conſtant certaine <hi>known voyce for the ſheep to follow,</hi> the <hi>Epitome</hi> of it, <hi>London</hi> can witneſſe at large: This <hi>Altum ſilentium</hi> is but a ſad off-ſpring of <hi>Reformation,</hi> eſpecially when the generall cry of it in thoſe <hi>common mouths,</hi> where there is <hi>vox &amp; praeterea nihil (and that not halfe ſo (weet as the Nightingale,)</hi> does moſt vehemently breath it ſelfe againſt dumb <hi>dogs,</hi> unleſſe this late <hi>ſacred ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> be <hi>deem'd extaticall,</hi> and a devout imitation of that <hi>ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> which ſometimes inwardly makes <hi>interceſſion for us with groans which cannot be uttered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But where I ſaid Prieſt, I may perhaps be asked, why I did not call him a <hi>Preſbyter</hi> or <hi>Elder?</hi> and it is not much amiſſe, if I had called him ſo; but then, let me briefly cleare in what acception I would take the word, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my information received from that learned impartial <hi>Indagatour</hi> of Truth, <hi>Joſ. Mead B. D.</hi> in his <hi>Diatribae,</hi> or rather from <hi>God by him,</hi> (for I may more immediately ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that here to a full explainer of <hi>Gods owne word,</hi> which <hi>Zanchius</hi> acknowledges as a due panegyrique to <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tom. 1. pars 2. lib. 4. c. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Ad ſingula ſophiſmata dignoſcenda, utiliſſimam nobis prabuit operam Ariſtoteles, imo Deus per Ariſtotelem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is in his Tractate upon 1 Tim. 5.17. <hi>Let the Elders that rule well, eſpecially they that labour in the word and doctrine.</hi> From whom I learne that the New Teſtament uſeth the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for the <hi>Miniſters of the Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments,</hi> that hence was raiſed the <hi>Saxon</hi> word <hi>Prieſter;</hi> and from that (neither from <hi>Jew</hi> nor <hi>Pope</hi>) the Engliſh word <hi>Prieſt:</hi> Hence ſome will have two ſorts of Elders, the <hi>Ruling-Elders</hi> from the firſt words, and the <hi>Teaching-Elders</hi> from the laſt; but the ancient Fathers, <hi>Chryſoſtome, Jerome, Ambroſe, Theodoret, Primaſius Oecumenius</hi> or <hi>Theophylact,</hi> as they had no <hi>Ruling-Elders,</hi> ſo from theſe words underſtood <hi>Prieſts</hi> onely: The words from the <hi>ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:114104:14"/>would be thus rendered, <hi>Let the Elders that rule well,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, chiefly thoſe of them who labour. So that there are <hi>two duties,</hi> but not <hi>two ſorts of Elders;</hi> ſo <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and other <hi>Greek Writers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Interpretation is, that the Apoſtle ſpeakes here of <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> conſidering <hi>both</hi> as <hi>Members of the Eccleſiaſticall conſiſtory;</hi> and then the words beare this, <hi>Let the Elders that rule well</hi> (whether <hi>Prieſts</hi> or <hi>Deacons</hi>) eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the <hi>Prieſts who rule and labour alſo,</hi> without this bee meant, no proviſion is made here for Deacons, which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable to be omitted, ſeeing the very <hi>Widows</hi> are cared for in the verſe before.</p>
            <p>Others admit <hi>two ſorts of Elders,</hi> but <hi>both Prieſts,</hi> the one <hi>reſidentiary,</hi> who were affixed to certaine Churches, and ſo did <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; the other of ſuch, that Travelled to preach the Goſpell where it was <hi>not,</hi> or to confirm it where it <hi>was</hi> preacht, to this latter ſort the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> may relate, being uſed by St. <hi>Paul</hi> in this very ſenſe, 1 Cor. 15.10. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>For it is manifeſt, he tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled much more then they all.</hi> Now whether a Text ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſo various expoſition, be a ſufficient (as it is the only) foundation for a <hi>New government</hi> never heard of in the whole Church of God, ſince the Apoſtles time, till this laſt age, He that can judge, let him judge.</p>
            <p>But what if from hence we alſo grant them, <hi>Lay-Elders,</hi> not <hi>Church-officers,</hi> but <hi>Civill Magiſtrates?</hi> So we read of the <hi>Elders of Iſrael,</hi> of the <hi>Elders of Judah,</hi> of the <hi>Elders of the Prieſts,</hi> of the <hi>Elders of the people;</hi> and then the ſenſe is, <hi>Let the Elders which rule well</hi> (even the Civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate alſo) eſpecially thoſe (Eccleſiaſticall Elders) <hi>that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the word.</hi> Is not this good ſenſe? And does not the Apoſtle begin this Chapter with an Elder in the larger ſenſe,<note place="margin">V. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Rebuke not an Elder, but intreat him as a Father, and the younger men as brethren.</hi> So St. <hi>James</hi> calls the <hi>Miniſters of the Word and Sacraments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ch 5.14.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as it were in <hi>diſtinction</hi> from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Elders of the Church being one,</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>Commonwealth</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:114104:14"/>another. Nor is this expoſition ambitious, as preferring the <hi>Elders of the Church</hi> before thoſe of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> for the name of <hi>Elder</hi> is never given in Scripture, to the <hi>ſupreame Magiſtrate,</hi> but to the <hi>ſubordinate</hi> only.</p>
            <p>I have Analiſed this peice from an heroicke pen, that I might not wholly fruſtrate HIS READER, but tender ſomething worthy his eye; I confeſſe my ſelfe, if I were <hi>diſplumed</hi> of my borrowed ornaments, and lookt upon in <hi>puris naturalibus</hi> as empty and naked as <hi>Aeſops</hi> Crow after Reſtitution made; but withall would have thee remember, that Truth alſo is wont to be limbed naked, and that the <hi>drawne colours</hi> are not put upon her, but are herſelfe. I count my ſelfe the more happy, whileſt I doe thus, <hi>Aliena vivere quadra,</hi> yet ſo too, that the taſte of my owne <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> does reliſh and approve the meat, though another provides the diſh, it is my owne <hi>ſtomach,</hi> which makes the <hi>concoction,</hi> and bids the <hi>dyet ſuſtaine me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next ſad object, which would be grieved for, is <hi>the utter change of our forme of worſhip in our publique prayers to God,</hi> and woe is it with the repute of our <hi>firſt and ſecond Reformers,</hi> whoſe Aſhes would deſerve very ill of mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full poſterity, fit to be racked out of their Urnes, and (if the Liturgy there be queathed to us, were indeed ſuch an <hi>Idoll</hi> as ſome blacke mouthes would make it) like the duſt of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> Calfe, to be ſtrawed upon the water,<note place="margin">Exod. 32.20.</note> and we as the Iſraelites be compelled to drinke of that brooke in our way, if their <hi>undiſcreet piety,</hi> their <hi>zeale without knowledge,</hi> had defiled our worſhip of God into ſuch an <hi>intire abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> as that it is left uncapable to be any other way refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, then by <hi>exact aboliſhment,</hi> by a very contradiction; no great need of a tough <hi>laborer</hi> to <hi>winnow</hi> that <hi>harveſt,</hi> and ſeparate the <hi>chaffe</hi> (if there be any) from the <hi>wheat,</hi> none, of a choice ſubtle head-peice to diſtinguiſh <hi>Truth</hi> from <hi>colors,</hi> and <hi>reality</hi> from <hi>errour,</hi> to purge out the one, and to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, refine, and approve the other, when the impartiall doom ſhall ſtrike at all, not tainted with a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allured with the <hi>beauties</hi> and graces of the beſt <hi>face</hi> amongſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114104:15"/>them, which could implead no exception from that ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping common ruine — <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na litura poteſt</hi> — ſhould the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Inquiſition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay. 14 23</note> or the <hi>Popes Bulls;</hi> nay, ſhould the <hi>Sword, and Alcoran of Mahomet</hi> (which have both beene wont to take their progreſſe together, and to ſucceede alike; the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coran</hi> has beene the <hi>Booke,</hi> but the <hi>Sword,</hi> the <hi>Pen</hi>) ſhould all theſe defloure our ſhoare with uninterrupted paſſage, the worſt of them could doe no more then <hi>put downe All;</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me if this ſounds like <hi>paſſion,</hi> and a boiſterous <hi>Surge</hi> furrowes the <hi>Calme</hi> face I promiſed, ſuch a loſſe affects the moſt <hi>ſenſible</hi> part, it <hi>touches</hi> to the <hi>quicke</hi> of the <hi>ſoule, quod in anima tenerrimum eſt,</hi> and the <hi>weight</hi> of it muſt ſqueeze out a word and a ſigh, <hi>tread the Wine-preſſe,</hi> and marke if it doe not <hi>bleed;</hi> thou can'ſt not ſo much as <hi>beat</hi> thy own <hi>drum,</hi> but it will <hi>ſpeak</hi> till it deafes thy eares with <hi>clamour:</hi> Yet all this <hi>noiſe,</hi> like thoſe <hi>ſobs</hi> after the <hi>departure of a beſt friend,</hi> doe not <hi>murmure</hi> at God, for any <hi>Inſtrument</hi> he ſhall pleaſe to begirt with his <hi>permiſſive Commiſſion to goe out, and deſtroy, to root out (I and branch out) and to pull downe our moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſires,</hi> becauſe of our former <hi>neglect</hi> of them; wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it <hi>juſt</hi> in him to let our <hi>after-ſins</hi> be an <hi>additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall puniſhment</hi> to thoſe which went before; ſo that what ever is here ſaid, is but an unreflecting bewaylement of our owne ſad condition, and I hope, as it is <hi>lawfull</hi> for us to be <hi>wretched,</hi> it is ſo too, to <hi>bemoan</hi> our ſelves, and not to <hi>let God alone</hi> (though we interpoſe not amongſt men) <hi>till he reſtore theſe bleſſings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>lawfullneſſe,</hi> nay the <hi>Energy of ſet Formes of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> becauſe I confeſſe my ſelfe too low of wing, and not pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niond for ſuch a ſlight, capeable of ſo much majeſty of <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, hiſtoricall, and ſcripturall reaſon,</hi> with which it is richly furniſhd by thoſe ſolid, ſubſtantiall pens, ſome of whoſe <hi>deliberations</hi> I have formerly peruſed, and ſome I have now by me (and thanke God for all, that I may give you the more <hi>light,</hi> and not <hi>eclipſe them,</hi> I ſhall impart to you the <hi>Streame</hi> and the <hi>Fountaine,</hi> their <hi>reaſons,</hi> and the <hi>Authours</hi> together, with ſome ſlender ſupernumerary ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114104:15"/>of my owne obſervation and greivance, though I well know this will only call backe your <hi>intent eye</hi> from the <hi>magnificent buildings, and ſtately inward ornaments</hi> to beg at leaſt one <hi>broken glance</hi> upon the <hi>homely disfigured out houſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where firſt, Mr. <hi>Mead</hi> will tell you,<note place="margin">In his Diatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bae pag. 1.</note> that our Saviours Prayer is preſcribed, not only as a <hi>Patterue,</hi> though ſo alſo, <hi>Pray thus,</hi> Math. 6.9. but in the very <hi>Forme</hi> of theſe words, <hi>when you pray</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſay,</hi> ſay theſe very words,<note place="margin">Luke 11. v. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Our Father,</hi> where tis marke-worthy that the delivery of this Prayer in <hi>St. Mathew,</hi> as part of <hi>Chriſts Sermon upon the Mount,</hi> was not upon the ſame occaſion, nor at the ſame time, as that in <hi>St. Luke,</hi> which was upon a ſpeciall <hi>motion</hi> of his Diſciples at a <hi>time</hi> when himſelfe had done praying; <hi>that of St. Mathew</hi> in the 2. that of <hi>St. Luke</hi> in the 3. <hi>yeere af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Baptiſme;</hi> whence it followes that his Diſciples tooke that in <hi>St. Mathew,</hi> for a <hi>Patterne</hi> only, and not for a <hi>Forme;</hi> had they taken it for a <hi>Forme</hi> alſo, they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready <hi>provided,</hi> and then neede not ſtill aske <hi>how to prays</hi> that they may take it for a <hi>Forme</hi> alſo, tis commanded to be performed <hi>in haec verba</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: This was a <hi>precedent</hi> and <hi>warrant</hi> to his <hi>Church</hi> to give the like <hi>Formes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next he tells us, the practiſe of the Old Teſtament is a good rule to follow in the New, and inſtances in thoſe 2 ſet Formes, appointed by God himſelfe, Numb. 6.23. <hi>On this wiſe,</hi> Deut. 26.13. <hi>Then thou ſhalt ſay I have brought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, that the Booke of <hi>Pſalmes</hi> was the <hi>Jewiſh Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi> or the cheife part of their <hi>vocall worſhip</hi> in the <hi>Temple,</hi> evidenc't by the <hi>Titles of the Pſalms,</hi> which commend them to the ſeverall <hi>Quires</hi> in the ſame, <hi>to Aſaph; to the Sons of Korah, to Jeduthun,</hi> and almoſt 40 of them to the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter Symphonia</hi> in generall; the like wee are to conceive of thoſe which have no titles, as of the 105. and the 96 Pſ. which wee finde in 1 Chron. 16.7. to be delivered by Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid into the hands of Aſaph and his brethren for <hi>Formes</hi> to thanke the Lord: wee our ſelves alſo, and all the <hi>Reformed Churches ſing the Pſalmes,</hi> not only as <hi>ſet Formes,</hi> but <hi>ſet
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114104:16"/>in Meeter (i. e.) after a humane compoſure;</hi> are not the <hi>Pſalmes ſet Formes of confeſſion? Of Prayer? Of prayſing God?</hi> If they ſay theſe are rehearſed only as <hi>Chapters,</hi> for <hi>Inſtruction</hi> (though my owne generall obſervation amongſt military men, and others diſinclined to our <hi>Liturgy,</hi> will reply them to be their <hi>devotionall,</hi> and not only their <hi>heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> part, elſe certainly they would give as favourable and ſubmiſſe an Audience to a <hi>Samuel,</hi> and a <hi>Matthew,</hi> as they doe to a <hi>Hopkins,</hi> and a <hi>Sternhold,</hi> they would not elſe be ſo <hi>familiarly covered</hi> to a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and an <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> when they <hi>appeare themſelves,</hi> and <hi>bare</hi> preſently to the advice of a <hi>David,</hi> when he only comes <hi>abroad</hi> by <hi>proxi,</hi> and the <hi>King is leſſened</hi> in the <hi>Ambaſſadour;</hi> unleſſe perhaps the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> is the more, becauſe, however he is now <hi>diſguiſed,</hi> he was <hi>once a King:</hi> Though I never forbeare to <hi>communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> in this <hi>Matter-Liturgy;</hi> yet I alwayes looke upon them <hi>cum venia,</hi> as an <hi>under-forme</hi> in the <hi>Schoole of Liturgy,</hi> whoſe skill I never yet heard any dare to equall, with thoſe grand <hi>Archi-Compilors,</hi> whom a very <hi>ſtake</hi> and <hi>faggot</hi> could not <hi>confute</hi>) yet no doubt wee may, and ought ſing the Pſalmes as they in the Old Teſtament did; the Churches of Iſrael uſed the Pſalmes, for <hi>Formes of prayſing, and invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting God,</hi> what elſe meane thoſe formes, <hi>cantemus Domino, pſallite Domino &amp;c?</hi> But there are two more direct, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Teſtimonies. 1 Chron. 25.1. It is expreſſely ſaid of the <hi>Sons of Aſaph and Jeduthun, that their Office was to Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie with a Harpe, to give thankes, and to praiſe the Lord.</hi> 2 Chron. 30.21. Wee reade that the <hi>Levites, and the Preiſts Praiſed the Lord day by day ſinging with lowd Inſtruments unto the Lord:</hi> and laſtly to leave no place for further doubt, wee reade, Ezra 3.10.11. that the <hi>Levits, the Sons of Aſaph were ſent with Cymbals to prayſe the Lord after the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of David King of Iſrael, and that they ſung together by courſe, in prayſing and giving thankes:</hi> Thus it was <hi>then,</hi> and thus it ſhould be <hi>now,</hi> for the Prieſt is called the <hi>Month</hi> of the people, whoſe <hi>Mouth</hi> he is not; if they are unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with what he ſayes. It ſhould be ſo for <hi>uniformity;</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:114104:16"/>for the Church being a myſticall body, cannot better teſtifie her <hi>unity</hi> before God, then in her <hi>uniformity</hi> in calling upon him. Thus farre he to whom I alſo refer thee in the ſame Tractate for an ample ſatisfaction to all <hi>voluntary extempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raneous prayer in publique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe I will adde ſome few reaſons (yet ſo that there ſhall be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an Ilyad of proof boſomed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſlender compaſſe of a Nut-ſhell) which I have bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In his practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme.</note> and which doe leſſe <hi>coincidere</hi> with the former, whoſe holy life, who ever knowes, will eaſily beleeve he is ſuch a man who does not <hi>ſtare à parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> is of no ſide, but <hi>Truths</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and that his <hi>reading</hi> had taught him the practize, and the practize wrote his booke.</p>
            <p>Where firſt let the practize of our <hi>dying</hi> Saviour give life to the legality of a <hi>preſcription,</hi> when he repeats the <hi>ancient</hi> words of his Father David, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> to quicken us to repeat His own words, who is now, <hi>Our Father in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>no-objection</hi> againſt a preſcribed Forme; for as it is lawfull to uſe them (after the uncontroled ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of all Churches, throughout all times) ſo it is lawfull to preſcribe them at ſome times, and for ſome uſes, for that a thing in it ſelfe acknowledged and proved to be lawfull, ſhould by being <hi>commanded by lawfull authority,</hi> become <hi>unlawfull,</hi> is very unreaſonable, unleſſe <hi>lawfull Magiſtrates be the only unlawfull things</hi> (which he that ſayes, will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce himſelfe at one againſt both <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi>) and at other times, to uſe other liberty is not forbidden, and ſo no <hi>Tyrany</hi> uſed upon our <hi>Chriſtian liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, by the great <hi>benefit</hi> that accrues to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation in having <hi>diſcreet well formed prayers,</hi> and ſo, not ſubject to the <hi>Temerity and impertinencies</hi> of the ſudden <hi>effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> and the ſame ſtill in <hi>conſtant uſe,</hi> and ſo, not <hi>ſtrange</hi> or <hi>new</hi> to them, but ſuch as they may <hi>with underſtanding</hi> go along with the Miniſter, and by the helpe of their memory the moſt ignorant may carry them away for private uſe (he
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114104:17"/>ſayes by their <hi>memory,</hi> not by their <hi>violence,</hi> as ſome late <hi>Ignorants</hi> have done, to carry away the <hi>Booke</hi> and all) and generally thoſe that want ſuch helpes, are by this meanes, afforded them.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, that by means of preſcribed <hi>Liturgies, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Faith and Charity is</hi> preſerved.</p>
            <p>To theſe let me adde another practize of our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and occurre to an objection, which may perhaps in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatuate ſome deceived minds (for I have heard this, to be the gain-ſaying diſcourſe of ſome who inſtead of the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> have ſet up a <hi>ſelfe-ſpirit,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) that though our Saviour prayed in the very words which King <hi>David</hi> penned, yet he never prayed againe the ſame prayer (a point of the new Creed amongſt <hi>Commander-Divines</hi>) but that he did this alſo, you ſhall finde in Mat. 26. v. 44. for he went away again, and prayed the <hi>third time, ſaying the ſame words;</hi> and that as a preparatory to his ſufferings which he ſaw at hand, for <hi>behold he is at hand that doth betray me,</hi> v. 46. perhaps to incourage mankinde, after their owne common guiſe, to give a more ample credit to imitation of the laſt words and actions of one ready to <hi>expire,</hi> as being then even amongſt our ſelves ſtript of all Pretence and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice, and nothing elſe but <hi>plaine ſolid Truths:</hi> ſo <hi>Lucretius</hi> tells us, that the <hi>World is mans Theatre,</hi> in which he perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates others, whilſt he expects a <hi>continued date of life,</hi> and is then only <hi>himſelfe</hi> when he begins to <hi>dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, if it be true (as he that doubts it is either an ignorant or a wilfull Atheiſt) that by a mans owne words he ſhall be juſtified, and by his owne words he ſhall bee condemned (by thy words, and by thy words, Mat. 12.37.) I cannot but preſume that <hi>thoſe words,</hi> if they have not the <hi>only,</hi> have yet a more <hi>eminent</hi> place in thoſe <hi>actions</hi> which more immediately concurre, and contribute to either our <hi>heaven</hi> or <hi>hell,</hi> and leaſt of all ſhall I make any ſcruple, that our prayers, either by the <hi>concomitancy,</hi> or by the <hi>defect</hi> of the <hi>qualifications</hi> required to them, are thoſe words, and amongſt ſuch, <hi>thoſe eſpecially,</hi> which are powred out by a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114104:17"/>
               <hi>publique Congregation,</hi> and in a place <hi>defigned for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</hi> (which ſome call the <hi>beſieging of heaven, and the taking it by violence, and the conquering of him who is Almighty;</hi> all of them holy and ſignificant raptures.) And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I take it is applicable that of our Saviour, uſhered in with that <hi>authoritatis formula, I ſay unto you, that if two of you ſhall</hi> AGREE <hi>on earth, as touching any thing that they ſhall aske, it ſhall be done for them of my Father which is in Heaven;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.11.</note> where though no doubt the prayer of a <hi>ſingle perſon</hi> (when that very ſingleneſſe is not evill, as ſpringing from an uncharitable <hi>ſeparate humour</hi>) is oft-times accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and hath its efficacy, yet, <hi>that God,</hi> who containes within his <hi>One-ſelfe</hi> a <hi>Trinity, (Numero Deus impare gaudet)</hi> does more liberally heare and grant the united prayers <hi>of many,</hi> which ſtrive to imitate <hi>God himſelfe,</hi> and in that very <hi>plurality</hi> to have but one heart and one minde; and though in that verſe but <hi>two</hi> are mentioned, <hi>that</hi> does onely magnifie the <hi>mercy</hi> of God, which will not bee <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned,</hi> though but for <hi>two's ſake,</hi> and yet he had rather be importuned by a <hi>cloud</hi> then by a <hi>drop,</hi> with whom it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly unacceptable that the people ſhould bee as clouds without raine round about, and only the <hi>Paſtours fleece,</hi> like <hi>Gideons be wet;</hi> as in <hi>Abrahams</hi> expoſtulation with God,<note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> the righteouſneſſe of the fifty had been more powerfull, though of the ten only had prevailed; to which interpretation the next verſe does direct and admoniſh me, where the <hi>Bell</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly calls for <hi>more company,</hi> and better it were if it could <hi>ring all in;</hi> for where <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three are gathered together:</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 20.</note> which <hi>agreement in prayer,</hi> as it comprehends the <hi>object,</hi> ſo that I can only pray with them, who pray only to <hi>God,</hi> and not with the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> which invocates Saints and Angells, God being the only object of prayer which our Saviour himſelfe hath taught me by a neceſſary excluſion of al others, when he commands me to pray, <hi>Our Father,</hi> which compellation I am well aware is incompatible to Saint or Angell, though they alſo are in Heaven; holy David hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed me in the ſame leſſion, <hi>Praiſe waiteth for thee O God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 65.1.2.</note>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:114104:18"/>
               <hi>O thou that heareſt prayer;</hi> ſo next, this <hi>agreement</hi> compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends the very matter, which if I am not well aſſured that it is ſtampt for <hi>Orthodox,</hi> by having pondered the whole ſubſtance of it before, and paſt my aſſent upon it, I may perhaps be there as an Auditour, I cannot as a ſupplicant; for, if I goe to Church onely with an <hi>implicite faith,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to pray, what ever he prayes that poſſeſſes the Deske or Pulpit, at beſt, is not this <hi>impliciteneſſe</hi> ſomewhat a kin to <hi>Popery,</hi> and may not my very <hi>Prayer be turned into ſin!</hi> by owing the <hi>inadvertenuſes</hi> and <hi>ſlips</hi> of him, who follows no other rule, but his <hi>peculiar ſudden dictates, Quicquid in Buccam Venerit,</hi> at leaſt gives them alſo leave to <hi>interpoſe;</hi> of which my ſelfe have beene ſeverall times a ſorrowfull witneſſe; If it ſcape that <hi>brand,</hi> does not the other <hi>twig</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> reach and ſcourge it home, which makes <hi>ignorance the mother of devotion?</hi> and what ſecurity can wee have, that in proceſſe of time, this very <hi>Surculus</hi> will not grow up to be an Arbor. Thus like <hi>Sampſons Foxes,</hi> though nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them will be called <hi>Foxes,</hi> which way ſoever their <hi>heads</hi> looke, their <hi>deſigne</hi> is <hi>one,</hi> to ruine and burne downe the <hi>graine</hi> whilſt it yet ripens, that which after its due growth would be our <hi>bread of life,</hi> and ſince it is true that we <hi>receive not what we aske, becauſe we aske amiſſe,</hi> doe we ever aske more <hi>amiſſe,</hi> then when we aske wee know not what?</p>
            <p>Or if I am not bound to let my aſſent waite implicitly upon his what ever <hi>ejaculations,</hi> I muſt then either not pray at all (like him in the Goſpell, who had not on the wedding garment, but was ſpeechleſſe) or elſe it muſt <hi>weigh and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate,</hi> and <hi>ſummon</hi> all <hi>ad ſtateram,</hi> I muſt give my <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> power to call them to the <hi>teſt</hi> before my <hi>affection ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe,</hi> and then when I have acknowledged <hi>this part</hi> or <hi>that period, right and uſefull,</hi> has not his feathered pace outſtript my <hi>leaden heele</hi> that I am at loſſe for many others, and may aſſoone purſue the trace of <hi>an arrow in the aire,</hi> though I cannot challenge to my ſelfe any large ſhare of quicke and ſharpe judgement, yet my very judgement from ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114104:18"/>of that <hi>reaſon</hi> which is <hi>common to all men,</hi> aſſures me that in <hi>this caſe,</hi> the beſt <hi>ſighted</hi> can ſteere <hi>no other courſe,</hi> though they may <hi>ſaile much faſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the laſt place (which is the moſt conſiderable number of Chriſtians in all places, in thoſe very <hi>Cities</hi> which are elevated to ſome higher degree of capacity, and whoſe ſoules coſt <hi>as good blood as the brighteſt in the Pariſh</hi>) what prop ſhall be put under the weake ones to uphold and inliven the devotion of the ordinary ſort of men? who if at all, muſt only pray <hi>per ſaltum</hi> becauſe they cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend (much leſſe comprehend) the <hi>matter,</hi> they are unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with at the firſt <hi>infuſion,</hi> nor the <hi>unwilling Erra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta's</hi> which the ableſt extemporaneous Oratour is lyable; for the <hi>beſt</hi> of them are but <hi>men,</hi> and ſuppoſe too, they were as Apoſtolicall and highly illuminated as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> (and perhaps ſome of them might have ſeen much more <hi>clearly,</hi> if they had not preſumed they had been already Eagles, <hi>Perveniſſent, niſi perveniſſe putaſſent</hi>) yet ſuch very men ought at leaſt to acknowledge,<note place="margin">Act. 14.15.</note> that they alſo are men of like paſſions with others; theſe congregations I muſt needs ſay it, doe claſh againſt that <hi>Rocke</hi> (and I pray God it never <hi>ſplit</hi> them) which they ſo ſeemingly abhorre, <hi>Incidie in Scyllam, cupiens vitare Charybdin;</hi> Their <hi>unknowne piety</hi> does reliſh unawares of the <hi>Romane infection;</hi> for I beſeech you, look <hi>calmly</hi> upon it, &amp; tell me ſeriouſly what is the great <hi>difference</hi> betwixt <hi>praying in an unknowne tongue, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I know not what in Engliſh?</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath coupled them in one ſenſe, in that queſtion (which in theſe dayes is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be asked againe) <hi>Elſe when thou ſhalt bleſſe with the Spirit, how ſhall he that occupieth the roome of the unlearned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.16.</note> 
               <hi>ſay Amen, at thy giving of thankes</hi> (for this very reaſon he ſhall not) <hi>ſeeing hee underſtandeth not what thou ſaieſt?</hi> nay, though <hi>all</hi> thou ſayeſt be <hi>good</hi> and <hi>ſound,</hi> yet there is ſtill an errour becauſe of his unreadineſſe to conceive before whom thou ſpeakeſt, <hi>For thou verily giveſt thanks well,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 17.</note> 
               <hi>but the other is not edified;</hi> the ſubſtance of the exception is the ſame in the matter, as in the language, intimated in the 14 v. <hi>my ſpirit
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114104:19"/>prayeth, but my underſtanding is unfruitfull;</hi> and immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hee applyes the remedy againſt this meerly ſpirituall praying, that though it is required, it is not onely required: what is it then? v. 15. <hi>I will pray with the ſpirit, and with underſtanding alſo,</hi> and in v. 21. he ſhews it to bee a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propheſied threat and judgement of God out of Eſa. 28.11. <hi>With men of other tongues, and other lips will I ſpeake unto this people;</hi> which unknown tongues (whoſe errour by his owne interpretation, conſiſts in the not-underſtanding of the people) he ſtamps alſo with the deplored marke of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion:</hi> upon this ground it is he decryes them, <hi>For God is not the authour of confuſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 33.</note>
               <hi>but of peace, as in all Churches of the Saints;</hi> and concludes all with that peculiar Scripture ſtile of willfull, acquired danger; <hi>but if any man be ignorant</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> loves his ignorance, and reſolves to be ſo, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding a whole Chapter againſt it) <hi>let him be ignorant,</hi> it is puniſhment enough; the whole Chapter throughout relates to the <hi>particular Churches</hi> and <hi>publique meetings</hi> for the ſervice of God, and the edifying of the people.</p>
            <p>It is too true, that in many, many places, where for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly every <hi>Peaſant</hi> of the vileſt ranke, who had <hi>ploughed out his ſix dayes, could, on the ſeventh</hi> pray to and praiſe his God with the <hi>heart and underſtanding,</hi> that now a vaſt number of them, <hi>great</hi> enough at leaſt to be pitied, have changed their upbraided <hi>ſincere Liturgy</hi> into a late <hi>lip-devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> (if they are ſuffered at all to ſpeake) and hollow <hi>eare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervice,</hi> which how unacceptably it will aſcend (if it aſcend at all, unleſſe perhaps the Prince of the aire carries it up as a witneſſe againſt them, and when he ſummes up his Bill of inditement, brings in the ſeverall <hi>auricular prayer,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring into a) <hi>cloud of witneſſes</hi>) to him,<note place="margin">Prov. 4.4.</note> who bids thee, <hi>Let thy heart retaine my words,</hi> and calls upon thee for that <hi>choiſeſt meat,</hi> diſdaining thy inferiour offalls, <hi>My ſon give it me</hi> (and let me tell you,<note place="margin">Prov. 23.26. Heb. 12 6.</note>
               <hi>He is his beloved whom he chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his ſonne whom he ſcourgeth</hi>) how much he rejects thy other unvalued ſcumme, the mouth of God himſelfe ſhall witneſſe, <hi>Wherefore the Lord ſaid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 29.13.</note>
               <hi>for as much as this people
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114104:19"/>draw neare me with their mouth, and with their lips doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour me, but have removed their heart far from me, and their feare towards me is taught by the precept of men. Therefore &amp;c.</hi> and ſo the curſe follows; and that God the Sonne is as little pleaſed with this ſhallow empty complement, you may conſult his owne Commentary upon thoſe words, <hi>Well did Eſaias propheſie;</hi> that is the Text,<note place="margin">Math 15.9.</note> and the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Sermon upon it is, <hi>That in vaine doe ye worſhip me;</hi> in vaine, when ye thus ſpeake; much more in vaine; when the <hi>ſilent lifting up of the hands,</hi> is the <hi>onely morning ſacrifice;</hi> I can lye in bed and doe that.</p>
            <p>But I have heard after all that can be ſaid, much rather after theſe ſlight lampleſſe attemps of mine (which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe iſſue from one that is <hi>weakly wel-minded,</hi> and hath no other imployment, but to ſit ſtill, and either write or ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate upon theſe diſtempers, and hath learnt, that ſo much declaimed up ſelfe-preſervation, to wring out thoſe <hi>drops</hi> which would be more <hi>dangerous</hi> while they <hi>bleed inwardly</hi>) ſome will compare a <hi>devotion framed when it is uttered</hi> (like the ſoule, which St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſayes, <hi>Infundendo creatur</hi>) to the whole walking upon a mans owne legs, and any preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion what ever, to a ridiculous <hi>paire of crutches,</hi> which though rumor faſtens upon a name too big to bee grapled with, I ſhall alſo ſpare to mention, both becauſe I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to yeeld my ſelfe an over-credulous captive to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, leſt the openneſſe of my ears might be accuſed of the <hi>ſlander,</hi> ſince to defame, would be a toilſome thriveleſſe trade, if men would heare leſſe greedily, and not ſet up this kinde of <hi>hearkning</hi> to <hi>out-ſacrifice the fat of Rams,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe though it were a meaſured truth, my very Schoole-refreſhments have civilized me into this <hi>Modum, Parcere Perſonis,</hi> that I ſhould not ſnatch at a ſhadowy repute from the diſgrace of any, <hi>Mihi de nullo, fama rubore placet, yet</hi> leaſt ſome men ſwallow it as a rationall fancie, I will a little <hi>melt</hi> off the <hi>paint,</hi> and ſhew you its <hi>contrary face,</hi> how it will looke moſt unlike it ſelfe, and halt out of your ſight from an apprehenſive ſhame of its owne <hi>lameneſſe,</hi> at length
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114104:20"/>only troubled that it cannot <hi>out-run the Chace:</hi> Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath preſcribed me a prayer, a very ſet <hi>forme;</hi> he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me that as a guide to my devotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherby I might tread upright; It is in this ſenſe, the <hi>foot</hi> of my ſoule, that by it, I may climbe thoſe ſteps in <hi>Jacobs</hi> ladder, which reach up to heaven; juſt as he hath beſtowed upon me <hi>fleſhy limbs</hi> to trace that earth which he hath <hi>given to the ſons of men;</hi> Hee hath alſo inabled me with a <hi>gift</hi> and power to frame other <hi>ſupplications</hi> out of that <hi>fruitfull forme,</hi> juſt as he hath imparted to me, out of that equall <hi>docility</hi> indulged to the compoſition of whole mankinde how to make to my ſelfe a Crutch, if he will be yet perverſe, and cry out ſtill againſt my <hi>preſcribed Iameneſſe,</hi> I ſhall ſatisfie my ſelfe in deeming it better, to <hi>enter into life thus halt or maim'd,</hi> rather then by having ſuch <hi>feet of mine owne</hi> to be <hi>caſt into everlaſting fire:</hi> But perhaps, our Saviours owne prayer may eſcape ſcandall free, and the blow be only meant at thoſe of the Church, becauſe they ſay, (I have heard ſome ſay ſo) the whole life of man muſt not be once guilty of repeating the ſame prayer twice; and yet that part of our Letany, <hi>O Son of David have mercy upon us,</hi> was ſo farre from being <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved</hi> by Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 10.1.17.48.</note> that I doubt not but the very <hi>repetition</hi> of it <hi>in the ſame words wrought the cure,</hi> for the importunate perſevering in his requeſt, under the very ſame <hi>formality,</hi> and crying ſo much the more, though many charged him that he ſhould hold his peace (though they had no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for ſuch a reſtraint upon his prayer) did give a preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant teſtimony of that ſtrong Faith, which our Saviour told him had made him whole, <hi>and immediately he received his ſight:</hi> And that other part in the <hi>Te Deum</hi> preſcribed to us, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God Almighty,</hi> was more cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully entertained by that <hi>Lambe which ſat upon the throne,</hi> and his copartners in divine worſhip, the <hi>Father and the Spirit</hi> (for I may conceive, there is a <hi>particular holy to each of them,</hi> or elſe the prayer would be in a manner ſaid <hi>thrice together</hi>) which gives me the ſame advantage becauſe the foure beaſts did <hi>not ceaſe day and night ſaying the ſame words,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev 4.8.</note>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:114104:20"/>concerning whom that <hi>reprooving</hi> prayer need not be uſed, which is wont to <hi>impute darkeneſſe to us, that God would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their eyes;</hi> for as they were <hi>full of eyes within,</hi> ſo none neede ſcruple but thoſe <hi>eyes were full of light, and illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and in the <hi>holy Euchariſt,</hi> where wee uſe the ſame words, we confeſſe them to be the <hi>voice of the Angels, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels, and all the Companies of Heaven;</hi> I ſhall never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how <hi>any Companies upon Earth</hi> have better learnt to <hi>pray,</hi> then <hi>all in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for the Church-prayers intirely as they lye (for I would only ſpeake of publique worſhip; each mans pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate devotions I leave betwixt God and his Conſcience, as having no key to any cloſet, but my owne) If wee looke u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the <hi>naturall indowments</hi> of any ſingle man, be they as Mountainous, as he ſhall pleaſe to thinke them, I cannot in any reaſon, but count it a deluded preſumption that he would prefer <hi>his owne unpremeditated fluencies,</hi> to the <hi>elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, joynt-reſults of ſo many learned men,</hi> who <hi>contrive ex inſtituto,</hi> where he but <hi>ſtumbles;</hi> or if the <hi>gift of the ſpirit</hi> be regarded, I ſhall never doubt, but God do's more plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully powre out his ſpirit upon the <hi>legally repreſentative Church,</hi> imploring his aid, then upon any <hi>one Member</hi> of it: nor is this, to <hi>ſhorten the hand of God,</hi> which ſure ſpreads it ſelfe <hi>farther</hi> in ſuch a <hi>univerſall benevolence:</hi> If he will ſtill like the <hi>fained impotent,</hi> not obtaining what he askes, hold up his very <hi>crutch</hi> againſt me (ſince, to a reſolved <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacy, a Sarcaſme</hi> is more <hi>operative</hi> then a <hi>Conviction</hi>) I ſhall only deſire him to turne <hi>Baker,</hi> as well as <hi>Canoniſt,</hi> becauſe, elſe himſelfe ſhould only feed on <hi>crutches,</hi> whilſt the other eates up <hi>legs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For theſe and many other reaſons, which you may more copiouſly imbibe from the obvious diſcourſe of learned men, then from the unaptneſſe of my hand to write, I would faine implore ſome <hi>liberty to tender conſciences,</hi> who are ſo well aſſured of the <hi>lawfulneſſe,</hi> and ſo much experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc't in the <hi>benefit</hi> of our <hi>Liturgy;</hi> and wee hope this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty will not be called <hi>licentionſneſſe,</hi> ſince wee rather
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114104:21"/>conceive it a <hi>bridle,</hi> then a <hi>ſpur</hi> to <hi>that,</hi> becauſe the property of <hi>that</hi> is to open an unlimited way for all to doe <hi>what is good in their owne eyes,</hi> (the uncheckt miſdemeaning garbe of the very people of God, <hi>when there was no King in Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el) and this fixes its eye upon the eſtabliſht Lawes made by Proteſtants in defence of Proteſtaniſme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 17.16.</note> 
               <hi>and calls in them to ſuccour:</hi> Tis St. <hi>Judes</hi> advice, <hi>after he hath charged you to keepe your ſelves in the love of God, looking for the mercy of our Lord Jeſus, that your ſelves would ſhew love and mercy to your Neighbour, that you would have compaſſion of ſome, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a difference;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 22.</note> thoſe, towards whom the difference is recommended, are they of a more <hi>tender nature then others,</hi> (as the late Annotations) and certainely no <hi>tenderneſſe</hi> of ſo ſupple a nature, as <hi>that</hi> of <hi>conſcience</hi> (declaring and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it ſelfe to be only <hi>conſcience,</hi> without any adheſion of <hi>terrene mixture,</hi> by the contented loſſe of all things elſe, then which there is no higher <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, imaginable of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, <hi>uningaged conſcience</hi>) which he that indeavours to <hi>force</hi> (there may be an <hi>indeavour,</hi> there cannot be a <hi>forcing</hi>) will <hi>torture</hi> and <hi>vexe it as a thing that is rawe,</hi> and make him <hi>cry out there is Death in the pot—Idem facit occidenti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this, and leave all men to conſider what that is, they carry within their <hi>breaſt,</hi> how <hi>blunt an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the keeneſt ſword</hi> will appeare, when it <hi>incounters the minde,</hi> which as no <hi>violence can kill,</hi> ſo neither can it <hi>informe.</hi> Thoſe who have paſt their <hi>Minority in Religion,</hi> and are growne up to the <hi>ſtature of men in Chriſt,</hi> may be charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly preſumed to have <hi>tryed, and approoved their worſhip by fixt Principles,</hi> which like the <hi>Rockes</hi> in the <hi>Sea</hi> are the <hi>ſame,</hi> and <hi>unmooved</hi> what ever <hi>Waves oppoſe, and breake themſelves in the tumultuous conflict:</hi> A <hi>Principle</hi> which I have already digeſted, is not the leſſe a <hi>Principle to me,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome other man delights in <hi>contrary Rudiments; the Milke of the Goſpel</hi> is not the leſſe <hi>ſincere,</hi> though it be not <hi>ſerved after the Geneva-faſhion;</hi> thoſe, whoſe <hi>moderne yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdayes conſtitution of Government</hi> require it ſo, let them have it, as it <hi>trills</hi> from the <hi>teat, drop by drop,</hi> unſtraind from
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114104:21"/>mixture of <hi>hayre and duſt, and godly filth, and much good may the drench doe them;</hi> for my part, I am not ſo eagerly bent, but I can ſtay the <hi>diſhing</hi> it, and I thanke God, I finde it <hi>non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth me never the worſe,</hi> becauſe it is the <hi>better cook't:</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the giddy people, whoſe only <hi>Principle</hi> it is to goe by <hi>none,</hi> or elſe who make <hi>Religion ſubſervient</hi> to their <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> and can be content to <hi>ſerve God</hi> ſo far forth as <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> will give them leave, ſuch whom the <hi>ſpeare</hi> which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened Chriſts ſide, can better teach to pray then Chriſts Spouſe the <hi>Church,</hi> I cannot but expect upon any new thoughts of a freſh alteration (to whom alteration it ſelfe, though it be to the <hi>worſe,</hi> is <hi>better</hi>) themſelves will be the moſt <hi>vehement Reformers,</hi> as counting <hi>that to calcine their Religion which makes it another,</hi> whom I looke upon, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotles Materia prima,</hi> which is <hi>Omulum for marum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers &amp; capax;</hi> when the next <hi>tempeſt</hi> aſſailes his houſe, doe but tell him, the <hi>Heavens chide at his falſe worſhip,</hi> and that the whole <hi>Fabrique</hi> will preſently <hi>intombe him,</hi> unleſſe the <hi>change</hi> of his opinions divert the <hi>ſtorme;</hi> tell him that— <hi>In te militat Aether, &amp; conjurati veniunt ad Maenia venti,</hi> and then doe but offer him a <hi>new platforme, you ſhall ſee and pity him, toſt too and fro,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>and carryed about with every winde of Doctrine;</hi> upon ſuch eaſie <hi>Articles,</hi> let him but <hi>ſave a houſe,</hi> and you ſhall gaine a Proſelyte; for my ſelfe, he whoſe <hi>proofes</hi> run in this <hi>Channell,</hi> will but <hi>beate</hi> the <hi>Aire,</hi> till my <hi>inward part is freely conquered,</hi> unballanc't with <hi>eſtate and advantages,</hi> and that I am glad it is ſo, I can but oppoſe to all other aſſaults that Theorem of Phalaris which ſwells with a Divine and Meaſured Truth, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And now to ſhut up all concerning the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, in a Cloſe, which I dare <hi>commend,</hi> I will give you in few the full of all which I can <hi>ſay</hi> or <hi>meane,</hi> you ſhall have them as they lie in <hi>Sir Edwin Sandys Europae Speculum pag.</hi> 214. without any of the leaſt intruding advantagious gloſſe, a man whoſe report hath hitherto ſtood up unblemiſh't a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Popery, which his very <hi>report</hi> do's ſo much <hi>blemiſh.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114104:22"/>England in their more ſober Moode, many of the Church of Rome will acknowledge to have beene the only Nation, that tooke the right way of juſtificall Reformation in compariſon of others, who have run headlong rather to a tumultuous Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation (ſo they conceive it) whereas that alteration which hath beene in England, was brought in with peaceable, and orderly proceeding, by generall conſent of the Prince, and whole Realme Repreſentatively Aſſembled in Solemn Parliament a great part of their owne Cleargy, according, and conforming themſelves unto it; no Luther, no Calvin the ſquare of their Faith; what publique diſcuſſing, and long deliberation did perſwade them to be faulty, that taking away, the Succeſſion of Biſhops, and Vocation of Miniſtery continued; the Dignity and State of the Clergy preſerved; the Honour and Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the ſervice of God not abaſed; the more ancient uſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Church not cancelled: In ſumme, no humour of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting contrariety, but a charitable endeavour rather of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity with the Church of Rome, in whatſoever they thought not gain-ſaying to the expreſſe Law of God, which is the only approveable way in all meere Reformations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At length I am arrived to the conſolatory part, which I propoſed as my deſigne, it hath the lucke of all ends to be <hi>firſt, and laſt, Primum in intentione, ultimum in executione,</hi> and falls out in its due finall place, as an <hi>Application</hi> after the explaining of the <hi>Doctrinall parts,</hi> which muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily have preceeded, as the <hi>Pracognita to this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where firſt, that I may eſcape the ſharpe retort of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damidas</hi> upon a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> who laboured to proove that <hi>only the wiſe man is the good Generall,</hi> he acknowledgeth the pith and ſubſtance of the Oration, with an <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> becauſe he never heard the ſhrill ſound of <hi>Trumpet,</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe <hi>I beare</hi> in my eſtate <hi>the markes</hi> of that wound, which I ſtrive to heale—<hi>Qua tolerata mihi, donec jam Aerumnaju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varet</hi> — and therefore can paſſe the <hi>probatum eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſon.</note> upon the Medicine, if it meete with a minde equally tempered.</p>
            <p>The holy charme is intended againſt <hi>diſrepute,</hi> and <hi>loſſe,</hi> for Gods ſake, and conſcience, <hi>that wee let not the receiving
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:114104:22"/>of honour one from another,</hi> hinder us from beleeving,<note place="margin">John 5.44.</note> that wee count the <hi>beſt honour</hi> (as indeed it is) to <hi>ſerve the beſt Maſter,</hi> both in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> our <hi>great God,</hi> and our <hi>good King; Nullum Theatrum Virtuti conſcientia majus eſt;</hi> that wee doe <hi>primas dare</hi> to our <hi>Creatour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tuſe. Quaeſt. Lib. 2.</note> and ſuffer not a peece of <hi>droſſie wealth</hi> (which God hath bid us to <hi>trample</hi> upon, and not let <hi>that to tread</hi> downe <hi>us,</hi> by the contemptible <hi>under-ſeate</hi> tis bred in) to <hi>divide</hi> with him, and <hi>Rivall</hi> his Honour; <hi>Impatiens Conſortis,</hi> is a <hi>maxime</hi> in the <hi>ſupreame Court above,</hi> as well as in the <hi>earthly Palaces;</hi> that wee be not only <hi>halfe beleevers</hi> and <hi>like thoſe many amongſt the cheife Rulers alſo,</hi> who meant no doubt, <hi>woudrous well, but becauſe of the Phariſes, they did not confeſſe him, leſt they ſhould be put out of the Synagogus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 12.43. Luk. 12.22.</note> 
               <hi>that we do not</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>hange betwixt</hi> 2, becauſe of <hi>food and rayment,</hi> and though wee ſeeme to propend heaven-ward, with the <hi>falling Mete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> grovell into the <hi>Daughill;</hi> that wee doe not ſhake off <hi>Providence,</hi> and inſtead of that, inſhrine a <hi>belly for our God,</hi> whoſe reward will be heavier, then that of <hi>Aarons Calfe,</hi> as much as the <hi>fire of Hell</hi> ſcorches more then that of thy <hi>Kitchen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any <hi>droopes</hi> under the load of his preſent diſtreſſe, St. <hi>James</hi> will reach out his hand to <hi>life</hi> him up;<note place="margin">Chron. 5. v. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Take my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Prophets for an example of ſuffering affliction, and of patience; behold wee count them happy that indure; they are already happy here, becauſe God deemes them worthy to ſuffer for his ſake, and if they indure unto the end,</hi>
               <note place="margin">St. Mat. 24.13. Heb. 12.2.</note> 
               <hi>they ſhall be ſaved, and be happy eternally hereafter.</hi> That <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſayes it, who, himſelfe indured the Croſſe, <hi>and dispiſed the ſhame, for the joy which was ſet before him.</hi> That <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who hath now, <hi>ſet the joy before us alſo,</hi> if wee will but <hi>despiſe the ſhame,</hi> imitating, and obeying both his <hi>example and command,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11.24.</note> to <hi>take up the Croſſe, and follow him to the Crowne of Glory.</hi> Bee the <hi>weather</hi> never ſo <hi>foule,</hi> he is but a bad <hi>worlds-man</hi> that will not venture <hi>abroad</hi> becauſe the <hi>wayes</hi> are <hi>deepe.</hi> When a faire <hi>Inheritance</hi> awaites the end of his <hi>Journey,</hi> a <hi>Rainy Day</hi> will not reſpite thy next <hi>Diſtrainer,</hi> and if thou mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114104:23"/>it well when he has prized thy laſt <hi>ſticke</hi> of wood, he do's but <hi>vertere ſterquilinium;</hi> let him <hi>ſpurne,</hi> as ſtately, as the <hi>fabled Cocke,</hi> and do thou take care that all his <hi>kickes and bruiſes</hi> do but <hi>illuſtrate,</hi> and <hi>brighten thy patience,</hi> he will ſtill hang downe his head, and only feed on <hi>Mucke,</hi> as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capeable to value ſo rich a Jewell, very like that <hi>Pearle in</hi> the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which thy meek <hi>ſelling of all thou haſt</hi> (ſelling it, in another Scripture Phraſe, <hi>for nought</hi>) to him who <hi>reſolves</hi> to have it, will be a great faire helpe to purchaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>James</hi> mentions none of the Prophets (but the Author to the Hebrewes tells you, <hi>They had triall of cruell mockings and ſcourgings, yea of bonds and impriſonments; they were ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they were ſawne in ſunder,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chro. 11.2.36.37.</note> 
               <hi>were tempted, were ſlain with the ſword, deſtitute, afflicted, tormented</hi>) he only tells you of a <hi>Job, and of the end of the Lord, that he is pitifull and of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercy;</hi> let us amaſſe all the afflictions which oppreſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of us, and if we look ſteadily, we ſhal find them all in one <hi>Job, Juncta fluunt, his oxen, ſheep, and camels taken away;</hi> his very <hi>children ſlaine;</hi> nay and (what was the greateſt plague Satan could inflict) he is robbed of the <hi>publique wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of his</hi> God alſo; <hi>boyles and the potſheard are</hi> his <hi>imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>company,</hi> he ſits downe in <hi>teares,</hi> and <hi>corruption</hi> and <hi>aſhes;</hi> he that hath the greateſt griefes hang upon him, let him ſtrictly view this <hi>glaſſe,</hi> and compare his with <hi>Jobs,</hi> how will his owne misfortunes ſlide into advancements, and his flowing ſoule melt into a compaſſionateneſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible of any <hi>ſelfe-diſaſter,</hi> and only <hi>tenderly afflicted,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Iob</hi> was ſo much <hi>afflicted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we looke nearer home, I can tell you of a Prophet whoſe Chriſtian courage out-faces and ſtrikes backe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, who hath atteſted to all the world, how far he is from ſhrinking under the calamities, which doe not <hi>confront</hi> but <hi>uphold him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">J.M.D.D.</note> that <hi>he ſhall count it as great a happineſſe as God can beſtow him, whilſt he ſtayes here on earth to call him to the ſtake, and let him fall a ſacrifice with the bleſſed Compilers of our Liturgy, to the long ſince Reformed Religion,</hi> a peece of ſo <hi>maſculine primitive Chriſtianity;</hi> worthy to be written
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:114104:23"/>in letters of Gold, or which is a <hi>ſtile</hi> more agreeable to the <hi>Aetas Ferrea</hi> in which we <hi>live,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pliny uſes the ſame word for a writing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument. Non minus agit ſtilus, cum delet, quam cum ſcribit.</note> unleſſe the Poets elegancy confute the life, and our owne ſad ſenſe more <hi>genuinely tranſlate</hi> it then any <hi>May, Non eſt vivere vita,</hi> to be <hi>graven with Iobs iron pen in a Rock for ever;</hi> which profeſſion of his (and how much does it become his <hi>profeſſion,</hi> not to <hi>dawbe,</hi> not <hi>feare,</hi> but meet the <hi>wolfe</hi>) joyned with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of thoſe many <hi>patient ſufferers</hi> in theſe dayes, whoſe meekneſſe, and <hi>acquieſcence</hi> in the <hi>glorious ruines</hi> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve them, is ſo remarkable, as if it would almoſt invert the <hi>Apoſtles ſenſe,</hi> and <hi>make chaſtening for the preſent alſo, not to ſeem grievous, but joyous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.11.</note> 
               <hi>yeelding the peaceable fruit of righteouſneſſe unto them which are exerciſed thereby, even whilſt they are exerciſed; and that by war;</hi> who count the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt loſſe</hi> of their lively hoods, a new preferment, <hi>Tantuſque malo fuit uſus in iſto,</hi> ſhould ſet a <hi>non ultra,</hi> to the deluge of <hi>Common teares,</hi> and wipe them away from off all our faces at their firſt eruptions while they are yet trickling downe: when the Apoſtles had ſent choſen men with <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> to ſuppreſſe a Sect, v. 5. they gave this teſtimony to fit their reception, that they were men who hazarded their lives for the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Act. 15.26. if, ſimply, obedience be better then ſacrifice, how much more acceptably will they fall to God, who performe both, whoſe very obedience ſhall make them a ſacrifice? In theſe laſt and <hi>perilous dayes,</hi> That precept of <hi>trying the ſpirits, whether they are of God,</hi> does equally concerne us, as the care of our owne ſoules; I cannot therefore but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you of the <hi>Characteriſticall marks,</hi> whereby you may know who is a true meſſenger of God, 2 Cor. 12.12. <hi>Truly the ſignes of an Apoſtle were wrought amongſt you in all pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> v. 10. <hi>I take pleaſure in infirmities, in reproaches, in neceſſities, in perſecution, in diſtreſſes for Chriſts ſake, for when I am weake then am I ſtrong, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. V. I become a foole in glorying;</hi> yee have <hi>COMPELLED</hi> me; which ſignes the late Annotations upon the Bible call Demonſtrations <hi>a ſigno, evident arguments, that he was indeed an Apoſtle of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:114104:24"/>Jeſus Chriſt; the reverend Diodate calls them the certaine and unreproveable arguments of St. Pauls full Office of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, and that the ſufferings which he indured, and overcame by faith, and conſtancy, were a ſigne of the Apoſtles LOY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ALTY, and of the preſence, and aſſiſtance of Gods spirit;</hi> faire Teſtimonies theſe, if none envy their application to the <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Fathers and Sons of the Church:</hi> I confeſſe it true, that I meet with divers in the <hi>London-Martyrology, dead with greife,</hi> and ſhould my ſelfe only greive for thoſe (paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by the many others, whom I reade <hi>Outed, Sequeſtred, Plundered, Impriſoned, Dead</hi>) but that I muſt in all charity preſume they did not greive for the <hi>weight,</hi> which ſunke them downe, downe to the very grave, but for the <hi>hands</hi> that layd it on. Writing after the <hi>faire, though bloody coppy,</hi> of the <hi>crucified Jeſus,</hi> who, though he forbad not the <hi>Daughters of Jeruſalem to weepe;</hi> yet he directed which way the tyde of their ſtreame ſhould run;<note place="margin">Luke 33.28.</note> 
               <hi>Weepe not for me, but weepe for your ſelves, and children,</hi> whoſe <hi>guilt,</hi> which I ſuffer for, do's <hi>murther me:</hi> I doubt not, but when <hi>Saul perſecuted the Church of God</hi> (and thereby, <hi>God himſelfe, Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me</hi>) beleeved <hi>that</hi> his <hi>duty,</hi> and I ſhall not ceaſe to pray for thoſe, who now doe <hi>errare, ſed bono Animo,</hi> that God would <hi>open their eyes,</hi> and uſe ſome <hi>Ananias Inſtrument</hi> (whom himſelfe ſhall pleaſe) that there may <hi>fall from them,<note place="margin">Acts 9.18.</note> as it had beene ſcales, and his grace</hi> which knowes no bounds, bee <hi>ſufficient for them alſo,</hi> that wee may <hi>vnite</hi> againſt the <hi>common enemy of truth,</hi> and no longer <hi>increaſe</hi> the forraine miſſe-call'd <hi>Catholique ſtrength</hi> by <hi>inteſtine diviſions</hi> (which render ſo many ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall men, ſo many diſtinct Churches, like Angels, amongſt whom each <hi>indiduum</hi> is a <hi>species</hi>) and in the meane while, ſo long as wee are bruiſed under Gods hands (till both the <hi>Mountaines ſmoke, and the Vallies tremble</hi>) let us humbly <hi>kiſſe that hand,</hi> and looke upon it, even whilſt it <hi>ſtrikes as a badge</hi> of his favour to us; for, it has ſometimes beene a curſe,<note place="margin">Ezek. 16.42</note> like that of <hi>finall dereliction, that God would make his fury towards thee to reſt, and his jealouſie to depart from thee,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114104:24"/>that he would be quiet, that he would be no more angry;</hi> O Lord, God, thou do'ſt <hi>puniſh</hi> us worſt of all, when thon <hi>letteſt us alone;</hi> thy <hi>anger</hi> is then <hi>greateſt,</hi> when thou wilt not <hi>vouchſafe</hi> to be <hi>angry;</hi> O Lord, let us <hi>run</hi> what toil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome race thou pleaſeſt, ſo that wee may <hi>obtaine;</hi> let the <hi>temptations be manifold</hi> ſo that the tryall of our faith, <hi>though tryed with fire, may be found unto praiſe, and honour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>and glory at the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> that the great <hi>Accuſer of the Brethren</hi> may himſelfe be weary in laying baites and traps in our way, and be glad to <hi>ſpare us a little, becauſe he ſhall perceive our ſoule is eſcap't as a bird out of the ſnare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 124.7.</note> and that his <hi>vanquiſht ſeducement</hi> dos but make us <hi>Birds of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe,</hi> and further our <hi>flight</hi> to <hi>Heaven,</hi> our <hi>ſuffering with Chriſt will</hi> be but a preface to our <hi>after-raigning with him,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> a <hi>Volume,</hi> without a ſubſcribed <hi>Finis,</hi> of <hi>writing this booke, there will be no end;</hi> and then let who will raigne here <hi>as Kings without us, being ſo rich and full in spirituall gifts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.8.</note> that our ſuperfluous inſtruction is counted but a <hi>drop</hi> to the <hi>River,</hi> and <hi>that,</hi> perhaps, a <hi>poyſonous drop</hi> to infect the whole River (for ſo vilely once were the Apoſtles e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed by thoſe, who <hi>heapt unto themſelves Teachers</hi>) whil'ſt Chriſt will hereafter, deigne us to ſit upon <hi>Thrones, in his incorruptible, and unbribed Kingdome; wherefore let us conſider him, that indured ſuch contradictions of ſinners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelfe, leſt wee be weary, and faint in our mindes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.3.</note> 
               <hi>the spirit of a man</hi> (whoſe contemplations have ſurvayd that exact Map of ſufferings) <hi>will Iuſtaine his infirmity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 18.14.</note> and if it be a <hi>wounded spirit,</hi> looke but unto the <hi>brazen ſerpent, and you ſhall live,</hi> he is that <hi>anointed,</hi> whoſe <hi>oyle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num 21 9.</note> will not only <hi>cure,</hi> but make thee <hi>chearfull;</hi> his <hi>blood</hi> is the <hi>oyle,</hi> and his <hi>ſtripes</hi> will <hi>heale thee;</hi> looke upon him, as he is thy <hi>head; if one member</hi> (the <hi>head</hi> eſpecially) <hi>ſhall ſuffer, all the members ſuffer with it; now yee are the Body of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12 27.</note> 
               <hi>and Members in particular;</hi> I ſhould ſuſpect my ſelfe no true <hi>Member,</hi> but a <hi>chip</hi> of ſome other block, fit <hi>fewell</hi> for <hi>hell,</hi> and <hi>dead whilſt I live,</hi> if I were ſo <hi>paralyticall,</hi> as not to feele when my <hi>head akes,</hi> if I had not this cauſe of ioy in my
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:114104:25"/>
               <hi>ſufferings that I helpe to fill up,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 1.24.</note> 
               <hi>what is behinde, of the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſt;</hi> Looke upon him againe, how his owne <hi>ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> ſweats out <hi>blood</hi> through every Pore, as being himſelfe more willing to <hi>powre</hi> it out, then the Souldiers <hi>thirſty ſpeare</hi> to <hi>bereave</hi> him of it, how his <hi>forward ſufferings</hi> ſpeake through every limbe of his panged body to the barbarous Jew, <hi>ſatiate ſanguine,</hi> and checke the <hi>delay</hi> of the <hi>thornes,</hi> and the <hi>nailes,</hi> as if it were never too <hi>early to fall an innocent expiatory ſacrifice for ſin;</hi> conſider the <hi>head,</hi> in which all the ſenſes meet, and combine, to make the torment as accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately <hi>rigid</hi> as a ſtudied <hi>Tyranny</hi> can <hi>invent;</hi> or a mortall <hi>man abide,</hi> and thou ſhalt finde, that <hi>no ſorrow was like unto his ſorrow,</hi> that thy owne <hi>ſecure penſiveneſſe</hi> is but a <hi>faint ſhadowy reflection</hi> to thoſe tortures, which like <hi>Rayes</hi> of darted fire, incirculed the <hi>Sun of righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great ſtile of theſe dayes honour, is the <hi>valiant man,</hi> but I may tell thee, to indure, is the niceſt <hi>proweſſe—Fortius ille facit qui miſer eſſe poteſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Martial</note> the Moraliſts cannot extend all the <hi>deedes</hi> of <hi>Alexander,</hi> to that height of gallant <hi>daringnes,</hi> in which <hi>Scavola</hi> committed his <hi>hand to the aſtoniſht flame,</hi> and went back a <hi>maimed Victour.</hi> Thus did his <hi>greatneſſe fall,</hi> whom the beguiled <hi>weapon spared—Hanc spectare ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Porſena non potuit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Ep. 3. c. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>St John tells us, that when Chriſt ſhall appeare,</hi> wee ſhall be like him, eſpecially if wee follow our <hi>vocation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>for even hereunto are wee called, becauſe Chriſt ſuffered for us, leaving us an example, that wee ſhould follow his ſteps,</hi> even <hi>thoſe</hi> in which he <hi>walks to Calvary;</hi> whoſe <hi>obedience</hi> if wee compare with it <hi>ſelfe,</hi> the virtue, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of his <hi>paſſiveneſſe,</hi> will out-ſhine all thoſe <hi>collected acts,</hi> the <hi>thinneſt Beame</hi> of which do's out-ſhine all the World; this is <hi>that</hi> wee <hi>hold by,</hi> and make our <hi>Plea</hi> for an eternall Manſion: All his <hi>active obedience</hi> was no more then to pay a debt, to which he <hi>freely entered into bond,</hi> after the <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge</hi> of which, <hi>himſelfe</hi> might paſſe to his former Seate in Heaven, (a very Seneca will give way to it,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nemo improbè eò conatur aſcendere, unde deſcenderat) doe this, and</hi> THOU <hi>ſhalt live;</hi> by the efficacy of his paſſive obedience, he did
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:114104:25"/>not aſcend <hi>ſingly</hi> as one perſon, but as the <hi>head</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> (and if the <hi>Head</hi> be <hi>taken out of the great waters</hi> the <hi>body</hi> will never <hi>drowne</hi>) as the <hi>firſt fruits of the harveſt (to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie the whole lump.</hi>) St. <hi>Paul</hi> linkes them all together:<note place="margin">Acts 26.23.</note> firſt, that <hi>Chriſt ſhould ſuffer,</hi> and then that he ſhould bee the <hi>firſt</hi> that ſhould <hi>riſe from the dead;</hi> the <hi>Croſſe</hi> gave him the <hi>precedence,</hi> but not the <hi>onelineſſe</hi> to heaven: And now, let who will upbraid an <hi>impoſed penury,</hi> the ſcorned iſſue of an unpolitique peece of <hi>dull honeſty;</hi> let him deſpiſe our <hi>plain integrity,</hi> becauſe it is not clad with the <hi>Silkeworms</hi> bowels; let him tell us, we are but weake and over-ſcrupulous, that demurre upon the <hi>wearing</hi> of a <hi>ſilken oath,</hi> that if we would but ſweare a little, with <hi>Peter,</hi> we might <hi>ſtand amongſt them and warme us,</hi> though we had rather <hi>bathe in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant tears,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 3 8.</note> and with St. <hi>Paul</hi> doe doubtleſſe (without ſuſpenſe or blending with the world) <hi>Count all things but loſſe for the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Ieſus our Lord (and of him crucified) for whom we ſuffer the loſſe of all things, and doe count them but dung, that we may win Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 10.</note> 
               <hi>that we may know the fellowſhip of his ſufferings, being made conformable unto his death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The very Heathens (amongſt whom, as we pray for the converſion of them that live, ſo we would be ſorry if the vertue of them that are dead, ſhould riſe up in judgement againſt us) ſnatch a buckler from the Law of Nature, againſt all the inſults and violencies of Fortune.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid quaeri Labiene, Jubes, An Noceat Viculla bonis?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lucan. l. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Fortunaque perdat, oppoſita virtute, minas?</hi> His Interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation will be reſolved into St. <hi>Pauls</hi> doubtleſſe.</p>
            <p>And it is Dogmaticall amongſt ſome of their Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, that a <hi>good man,</hi> though he <hi>fryes and lows in Perillus-Bull,</hi> may indeed be <hi>ſcorcht,</hi> but he cannot be unhappy, <hi>Marius capi poteſt, animus capi non poteſt;</hi> and ſhall we hang downe the Bull-ruſh head, where the <hi>perſecution</hi> is <hi>leſſe,</hi> and the <hi>remedy greater?</hi> not a <hi>notion,</hi> but a <hi>God</hi> to beare us up? to <hi>walke with us in the fiery ovens, and to breake our bonds in ſunder?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:114104:26"/>
            <p>Above all, let us take ſpeciall heed, that wee murmure not at God, becauſe we ſuffer unworthily; it is ſo in thoſe particulars, for which we mourne, if wee looke downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward only, and forget our <hi>Osſublime;</hi> but then our other high ſinnes have cryed out to God for theſe Juſt plagues, <hi>Quicquid vult Deus ideo bonum eſt, quia Deus vult,</hi> though we were inſpired with ſuch an <hi>Idea innocence,</hi> in which <hi>Adam</hi> ſtood, yet the <hi>Potter</hi> may breake his <hi>veſſel</hi> when he pleaſe, <hi>May he not doe what he will with his owne, and it is better,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3 17.</note> 
               <hi>ſince the will of God is ſo, that we ſuffer for well-doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Socrates</hi> wife (not much unlike to <hi>Jobs</hi>) would ſtir up his indignation againſt the ſentence of death, with That <hi>Faeminine provocative,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Hee returnes a milde check, and confutes her error out of her own mouth, raiſing a fort of patience from that, which ſhee meant a <hi>Canon</hi> againſt it, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; alas fond woman! wouldeſt thou have me <hi>deſerve to dye?</hi> and <hi>S. Peter</hi> tells us, <hi>This is thanks-worthy, if a man, for conſcience towards God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ep 2. c. 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>indure griefe, ſuffering wrongfully;</hi> and doſt thou repine, as at a <hi>ſtone,</hi> when thou ſhouldeſt give thankes for <hi>bread?</hi> It is not the nature only, but the <hi>ſeaſon</hi> of God, to ſuſtaine us in his owne cauſe. To <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;<note place="margin">Ariſtot. de Rbetorica l. 2. cap. 5.</note> He that knows how to <hi>beare,</hi> knows no ſuch thing, as an affliction (though undeſerved) as counting him only <hi>wretched</hi> that is <hi>ſinfull;</hi> It was <hi>Bions</hi> ſpeech, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, He that grieves at the harſh for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, when his <hi>untoucht conſcience</hi> does not <hi>ſmart,</hi> is his owne <hi>Tormentour,</hi> and hath great need to aske <hi>himſelfe</hi> to have <hi>mercy upon him: Iob,</hi> (whoſe patience we were bid remember) <hi>etiamſi occiderit,</hi> will truſt in God, though hee ſtay him. <hi>Abraham</hi> (to whom we would all be intituled as he is, <hi>Father of the faithfull</hi>) goes further, <hi>poſt quam occiderit;</hi> He will, by the <hi>probatory command</hi> of God, <hi>ſlay his ſon Iſaac,</hi> and yet <hi>beleeve</hi> and <hi>hope,</hi> though beyond hope, that this ſlain Iſaac ſhall have iſſue, like the ſands, when the only progeny which Nature could promiſe, would be the <hi>numerous duſt,</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:114104:26"/>into whoſe Fractions his body ſhould reſolve, and (like the prodigious <hi>Viperine iſſue</hi> of our <hi>mother Church</hi>) <hi>holy</hi> worms firſt bred out of him, and then devoure him; the wormes and the duſt would bee the children and the Grand-Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p>It were ill with us, if our owne contemplations could dive no further into that <hi>piece</hi> of the Apoſtle, <hi>Whom the Lord loveth he chaſteneth;</hi> nay not ſo farre,<note place="margin">De malis quae videntur bonis accidere.</note> as the Paraphraſe of a remote unchriſtian <hi>Seneca</hi> hath done, <hi>Hos itaque quos probat Deus, quos amat, indurat, Recognoſcit, exercet;</hi> and that we could not as well diſtinguiſh in truths of <hi>poſitive divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> as he in thoſe of <hi>naturall,</hi> who counts nothing more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardable then that we doe not, like thoſe <hi>beaſts</hi> which are only led by the eye, follow the <hi>Herd</hi> that goes before,<note place="margin">De vitâ beatâ C. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Non qua eundum, ſed qua itur:</hi> it will be well with us, if wee ſtand ſeparate from the crowd, and not reſolve upon any tearmes to joyne iſſue with the <hi>beaſts of the people,</hi> if wee learne not of the <hi>people</hi> what we ought to <hi>know,</hi> and how to <hi>live;</hi> but now (it is his owne complaint) the <hi>people</hi> is the Bulwarke of defence to their owne <hi>depraved opinions;</hi> and it was Gods, before him, <hi>The Prophets propheſie falſely, and my people love to have it ſo,</hi> Jer. 5.31. Humane affaires ſtand not ſo upright,<note place="margin">Cap 2. And in his 108. Ep. Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Honeſti Diſſuaſor.</note> as that the beſt things ſhould pleaſe the moſt, <hi>Argumentum peſſimi turba eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt all which contumelies and outrages of the <hi>people,</hi> we only buckle to our ſelves the primitive weapons, <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; lacrymas;</hi> the only <hi>Militia,</hi> in which we deſire to poſture the <hi>inward man</hi> is the <hi>whole armour of Chriſt,</hi> that armour which we beare and weild in the defence of All, and with which, as Members only of the <hi>Church</hi> Militant,<note place="margin">Mat. 5 44.</note> and ſuch, who love our enemies, and pray for them that deſpitefully uſe us, we fight for thoſe who fight againſt us; Let them ſtrive on to make us weep, and hautily preſume that this very <hi>remedy</hi> addes to our <hi>griefe (lacrymis egeritur dolor)</hi> whilſt Gods holy Spirit ſhall teach us how to mingle a prayer with our <hi>teares,</hi> and ſhall put the one into his <hi>bottle</hi> and the other into his Booke; whilſt God himſelfe ſhall tell
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:114104:27"/>us, <hi>That though we ſow in teares, and goe on our way weeping,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>yet ſince we beare forth good ſeed, we ſhall reap in joy, and bring our ſheaves with us:</hi> Thoſe <hi>teares,</hi> and that <hi>weeping</hi> will be as the firſt and latter raine, to prepare and <hi>ripen thoſe ſheaves,</hi> and in the end, the <hi>valleyes</hi> (thoſe againſt which the lofty hills have lifted up their heads) ſhall ſtand ſo thicke <hi>with corne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 65.14.</note> 
               <hi>that they alſo ſhall laugh and ſing,</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves partakers of the joy they create.</p>
            <p>Nature it ſelfe, by her dim light, takes aime from hence to preſſe towards the marke, forgetting the dangers which are behinde, and reaching forth unto the things which are before,<note place="margin">Philip. 3. 13.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, we are <hi>already</hi> partakers of the reward;<note place="margin">Phalaris Ep. 130.</note> for what the Moraliſts ſay of vertue <hi>in genere,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> brings down to her beſt ſhape, and complexion, in which ſhe can parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly appeare, that the ſuffering vertue is <hi>ſibi pramium,</hi> what ever malignant influence the ſpite of man thinks hee can breathe upon it, it is ſtill a <hi>reward</hi> and a <hi>benevolence,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this,<note place="margin">Phili. 1.28.29.</note> 
               <hi>Not being terrified by our adverſaries, does open to us the gate of heaven; for it is an evident token of ſalvation and that of God: unto us it is given in the behalfe of Chriſt not only to beleeve</hi> (thats no ſuch wonder in this age, every one hath faith at will) <hi>but to ſuffer for his ſake;</hi> nor is the Spirit <hi>which blows where it liſts,</hi> intailed only upon thoſe, who inflict theſe <hi>benevolences</hi> and <hi>rewards,</hi> &amp; <hi>gifts</hi> (for thus, that God, by whoſe wonderfull providence, <hi>all things work together for good to them who feare him,</hi> and feare nothing elſe,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.14.</note> does transform miſchief into a portion) <hi>We alſo who are reproacht for the name of Chriſt, happy are we, for the Spirit of glory and of God reſteth upon us:</hi> the tryall is made, and I hope it appeares, that we are men gifted by the Spirit of God at leaſt to ſuffer; Be they of the ſmalleſt ſize, yet <hi>Dona Regalia, quantumvis parva, evileſcere ignorant,</hi> one drop of ſeaſonable raine, which otherwiſe is at beſt but common water, and perhaps <hi>tempeſtuous</hi> too, is thus conſolidated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>Iewell:</hi> If thou wouldeſt be winged for Heaven, the <hi>bird of the aire</hi> will teach thee, at each drop to looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:114104:27"/>and articulate her ſilent praiſe into a <hi>digitus Doreſt hic,</hi> may that it is his <hi>whole open hand, and filleth us with bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings:</hi> for behold this is no ſcantling, parſimonious dowry, it is Sanctuary-meaſure, ſhaken and heapt together,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>For our light affliction, which is but for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternall weight of glory;</hi> ſo that I can hardly perſwade my ſelfe to let it bee called <hi>Affliction,</hi> though but a <hi>light one,</hi> though but for a <hi>moment,</hi> not onely, <hi>It is good for me that I have been afflicted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 23.4.</note> but <hi>though I walke through the valley of the ſhadow of death;</hi> I <hi>will feare no evill</hi> (in that very walke) <hi>for thou art with me</hi> (and ſo is in ſome meaſure a <hi>heaven here,</hi> when <hi>God is with me</hi> like <hi>that hereafter,</hi> when I ſhall be <hi>with God</hi>) <hi>Thy rod and thy ſtaffe,</hi> they doe <hi>already comfort me,</hi> and call for a returne of grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; there muſt be (like a <hi>grace</hi> after the <hi>voyder</hi>) a <hi>bleſſed be the Name of the Lord when he alſo taketh away,</hi> as well as when <hi>he gives us Angels food;</hi> nay this very <hi>bleſſed</hi> is that <hi>food,</hi> for as, to <hi>Chriſt upon earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 4.34.</note> 
               <hi>to doe the will of him that ſent him,</hi> ſo to the <hi>Angels in heaven</hi> (who take their name and office from this <hi>Miſſion</hi>) to <hi>praiſe his name is their meat and drinke—Pudeat tanto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>a velle caduca; Quid Calo dabimus? What ſhall we render unto the Lord?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Manil.</note> 
               <hi>we will take the cup of ſalvation, and call upon the name of the Lord:</hi> nay though that other cup, and the dregs thereof,<note place="margin">Pſ. 125.13.</note> 
               <hi>which muſt not paſſe from us,</hi> be the <hi>way</hi> to it; if with holy confidence we can affixe our <hi>fiat,</hi> though a <hi>veruntamen</hi> goes along with it, it will be a marke of Majeſty, that we are a Royall Prieſthood, eſpecially when we imploy our ſelves in that moſt prieſtly office of bleſſing the Lord himſelfe, and giving thanks in all things <hi>(Deo nullis rebus indigenti, poſito extra deſiderium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca Tom. 2 lib. 2. cap. 30.</note> 
               <hi>referre nihilominus gratiam poſſumus)</hi> and then quarrell with our owne giving of thanks, as a too low, and diſproportioned acknowledgement, impeaching that it ſelfe of ſome Ingrate Mixture, <hi>Dignas ſed pendere grates, hand mortale opus eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude,<note place="margin">Stat. lib. 22.</note> 
               <hi>The heavens indeed may rejoyce, and they that dwell in them</hi> (the ſoules of the Saints there, are ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:114104:28"/>as from their <hi>bodies,</hi> ſo from the <hi>diſtractions</hi> and <hi>unſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledneſſe in their worſhip;</hi> which ſhake the <hi>Communion</hi> and divide the <hi>Remnant</hi> of the Saints, who ſtill weare their earthly Tabernacles; <hi>This is the woe to the inhabitants of the Earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 12.12.</note> 
               <hi>and of the Sea, for the devill is come downe amongſt us of theſe laſt dayes, having great wrath, becauſe he knoweth that he hath but a ſhort time:</hi> And I perſwade my ſelfe, hee ſpends all his ſubtilty upon this laſt Stratagem, how to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and cheriſh a conſtant fewdand diſcontent, by <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> that <hi>truth,</hi> which he knows muſt be reſolute, and by <hi>protecting error</hi> and <hi>miſtakes,</hi> with <hi>ſtrength</hi> of <hi>Armes</hi> and <hi>colour of Law,</hi> which thus fortified, he knowes will bee Reſolute.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Lord, the hope of Iſrael, the Saviour thereof in the time of trouble; why ſhouldeſt thou be as a man aſtonied, as a mighty man that cannot ſave!</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Quid refert, Dictis ignoſcat Mutius an non?</q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 1. line 24. read into. p. 4. l. 4. r. it out ballance. p. 5. l. 33. r. waves. ibid. l. proud. ibid. p. l. ult. vanities. p. 6. l. 5. Embry of wims. p. 7. l. 3. <hi>Iuratus.</hi> ib. p. l. 8. lay. p. 27. l. 7. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. b. p. l. 28. once. p. 30. l. 10. ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. ib. p. l. 14. <hi>branch.</hi> p. 31. l. 13. adde to</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:114104:28"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
